<folder xmlns:fn="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions"
        xmlns:uuid="java:java.util.UUID"
        xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
   <Title>Document</Title>
   <folder ptx="chapter" xml:id="SNAME_Electric_Systems">
      <Title>Electric Systems</Title>
      <folder ptx="introduction">
         <Title>introduction</Title>
         <item>
            <p>This chapter is adapted from <pubtitle>Introduction to Practical Marine
        Engineering</pubtitle>, SNAME 2005.</p>
         </item>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section" xml:id="Fundamentals_of_electricity">
         <Title>Fundamentals of electricity</Title>
         <item>
            <p>Electricity is associated with the accumulation or the flow of electrons, which are
      negatively-charged, subatomic particles. Static electricity is caused by the accumulation of
      electrons, as might occur from rubbing hard rubber on a wool carpet. The resulting static
      charge of the stored electrons might then be released suddenly as a spark. In a more useful
      form of electricity, the electrons flow through wires to energize light bulbs and computers
      and to turn the shafts of motors.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>As long as a complete electric path or circuit is available, electron flow can be initiated
      and sustained in a number of ways, including chemical reaction and magnetic induction.
        <term>Batteries</term> and <term>fuel cells</term> cause electron flow by chemical reaction.
      For most applications <term>alternators</term> or <term>generators</term> are used to produce
      electron flow by magnetic induction, in which the mechanical power output of an engine is used
      to drive conductors through a magnetic field, inducing an electron flow In the conductors.
      Electron flows can also be created by <term>thermocouples</term> and <term>photovoltaic
        cells</term>, which respond to heat and light, respectively. Thermocouples are commonly used
      to generate electric signals for temperature measurement. Fuel cells and photovoltaic (or
      solar) cells have been used in low-power applications for years but are becoming more common
      and more capable of higher-power applications.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Electrons flow from areas of higher electron concentration (negative charge) to areas of
      lower electron concentration (less negative charge) if a conductor path is established. The
      conductor can be solid, like a copper wire, but liquids, such as salt water and mercury, and
      ionized gasses, can also conduct electricity. The effects of electron flow are recognizable
      and include, as examples, heating of the conducting wire element of an electric heater,
      causing a magnetic field around the conductors in an electric motor to produce mechanical
      torque, and heating of the ionized gas in a fluorescent lamp to produce light.</p>
         </item>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section" xml:id="Electrical_terms">
         <Title>Electrical terms</Title>
         <folder ptx="introduction">
            <Title>introduction</Title>
            <item>
               <p>Engineers do not normally speak of flowing electrons but rather of electric
          <term>current</term>. Current is an imaginary stream that flows from the less negatively
        charged area (more positive) to the more negatively charged area (less positive). That is\s,
        the direction of the current is opposite to the electron flow. This convention was adopted
        because it is easier to think of a flow going from a higher level (more positive) to a lower
        level (less positive). Current flow is normally given the symbol <m>I</m> and is measured in
        units of <term>amperes</term>, usually abbreviated to <term>amps</term>. Current in amperes
        is analogous to fluid flow in gallons or liters per minute.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The force used to push current through a conductor is the <term>electromotive force
          (emf)</term> or <term>potential</term>. It is measured in units of <term>volts</term> and
        identified by the symbol <m>V</m> or <m>E</m>. The fluid analog of the electromotive force
        in volts is pressure in psi or pascals.</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection">
            <Title>Direct current vs. alternating current</Title>
            <item>
               <p>Electricity may be supplied as either <term>direct current</term> (DC) or <term>alternating
          current</term> (AC). DC flows in only one direction in the conductor because the potential
        always acts in the same direction. Current originating from a battery in a flashlight and
        flowing to the bulb is an example of DC. The current flows from the positive terminal of the
        battery, through a circuit consisting of the switch, the bulb, and the conductors, to the
        negative terminal of the battery. Only the <term>resistance</term> (to electron flow) of the
        circuit limits the current. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>With alternating current the driving potential (or voltage) continually reverses direction,
        forcing the current in the circuit to continually reverse direction as well. The voltage
        takes the form of a sine wave as shown in <xref ref="fig_24_1_png"/>, rising first to a
        positive peak value as shown, then falling through zero to an equal negative peak value. As
        a result, the current first flows in one direction, peaks, slows, stops, reverses direction,
        increases to an equal peak value in the other direction, slows, stops, and resumes its flow
        in the original direction. In the United States the standard generating systems produce
        alternating current that reverses with a <term>frequency</term> of 60 cycles per second
        (cps), commonly referred to as 60 <term>cycles</term> or 60 <term>Hertz</term> (Hz). In
        Europe and Japan, the standard is 50 Hz.</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection">
            <Title>Resistance and resistance <q>loss</q>
            </Title>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <term>Resistance</term> to current flow is symbolized by <m>R</m> and is measured in units
        of <term>ohms</term>. Resistance can be calculated by <term>Ohm's Law</term>: if <m>E</m> is
        the voltage and <m>I</m> is the current, <me>R= \frac{E}{I}</me>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The magnitude of the resistance of a conductor is affected by the ease with which electrons
        (current) flow in the material. If electrons flow easily the material is said to have low
        resistance. Copper is a better conductor than steel, and is used in most power applications.
        The resistance also depends on the available area through which the electrons flow, and on
        the conductor length. As with fluid in a pipe, the narrower or longer the path, the more
        difficult it is to push the electrons through. Since most electric conductors are round, so
        that area is proportional to diameter squared, conductor area is often abbreviated to
        circular mils, where a mil is 0.001 inch, and a circular mil is the diameter squared. As an
        example a wire of 0.100 inch (100 mil) outside diameter is said to be a 10,000 circular-mil
        wire. Engineers often identify a conductor by its <term>American Wire Gage</term> (AWG)
        number. In this system the higher the number, the smaller the diameter, so that #12 wire is
        thinner than #10 wire.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Just as friction and other resistance to fluid flow in piping results in a <q>loss</q> of
        energy, so does the resistance in a conductor result in a <q>loss</q>. This <q>loss</q> is
        proportional to the square of the current, multiplied by the resistance: <me>\text{
          resistance "loss"} = I^2 R</me>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Because it is a function of the current squared, a modest increase in current in a
        conductor results in a much larger <q>loss</q> of energy. This <q>loss</q> manifests itself
        as heat.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The unit <term>megohm</term> is a resistance of one million ohms and is used to express the
        resistance of electric insulation.</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection">
            <Title>Magnetic field</Title>
            <item>
               <p>An electron flow, or current, is always surrounded by a magnetic field. When a conductor is
        wound into a cylindrical coil, the magnetic field that will be formed will be oriented along
        the axis of the cylinder. One end of the coil will act like the north pole of a permanent
        magnet, and the other end, like the south pole. The coil is therefore an
          <term>electromagnet</term>. </p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection">
            <Title>Impedance</Title>
            <item>
               <p>With alternating current, the electron flow is opposed not only by the resistance but also
        by an additional factor, the reactance. Reactance is caused by the response of the circuit
        to the cyclic fluctuations of the alternating current and voltage, and may be further
        categorized as inductive reactance or capacitive reactance. The sum of the resistance and
        the reactance is the <term>impedance</term>
                  <m>Z</m>, and has units of ohms. Impedance is defined as: <me>Z= E/I</me>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The magnitude of the impedance depends on factors that include the characteristics of the
        components in the circuit and the frequency of the current.</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection">
            <Title>Open circuits, short circuits, and grounds</Title>
            <item>
               <p>An <term>open</term> in an electric circuit occurs where the conducting path has been
        broken, stopping the flow of current. An open occurs when a switch is opened, or a wire
        breaks or becomes disconnected.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>A <term>short circuit</term> occurs when the current path is bridged, allowing the current
        to bypass one or more components, for example, when two conductors accidentally touch.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>A <term>ground</term> occurs when an electric circuit is accidentally or intentionally
        connected to a very low potential sink, like a ship's hull or the sea. A common example of a
        ground occurs when insulation on a conductor breaks down, allowing the conductor to contact
        the adjacent metal housing or structure.</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section" xml:id="Electric_power">
         <Title>Electric power</Title>
         <folder ptx="introduction">
            <Title>introduction</Title>
            <item>
               <p>The energy of flowing electrons is a power source that can be used do work in an electric
        motor or can generate heat as in an a toaster element. The unit of power associated with
        electric devices is the <term>watt</term> (W), which is the power produced when one ampere
        of current is pushed through an electric circuit by one volt of electromotive force (a
        potential difference). In a similar manner, hydraulic power is developed when a flow of
        fluid is pushed through a fluid circuit by pressure difference. Since the watt is a
        relatively small amount of <term>power</term>, <term>kilowatts</term> (kW) and
          <term>megawatts</term> (MW) are commonly used. One kW is equal to 1000 W, and one MW
        equals 1000 kW.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The law of conservation of energy dictates that electric energy or power can be converted
        to mechanical power or to heat, and vice versa. If the conversions were complete, one kW of
        electric power would provide a kW of mechanical power or a kW of heat. In familiar units,
        these approximate energy equivalents are listed below: <md>
                     <mrow>746 \text{ W} = 0.746 \text{ kW} = 1 \text{ hp}</mrow>
                     <mrow>1 \text{ kW}= 1.340 \text{ hp}</mrow>
                     <mrow>1 \text{ kW}= 3412 \text{ Btu/hr}</mrow>
                  </md>
               </p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection">
            <Title>Power from direct current</Title>
            <item>
               <p>In a DC circuit, where the voltage and current are at constant, steady values, the power in
        kW can easily be calculated as the product of voltage and current in amps: <me>P = E I
        </me>
               </p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection">
            <Title>Power from alternating current</Title>
            <item>
               <p>In an AC circuit the power cannot be calculated so easily because first, both voltage and
        current fluctuate in magnitude and direction in sinusoidal patterns, and second, because the
        voltage and current do not necessarily act in unison, as shown in <xref ref="fig_24_1_png"/>. To account for the cyclic variation in magnitude of voltage and current, an averaged
        value is used, called the <term>root-mean-square</term> or <term>rms</term> value. See <xref ref="fig_24_3_png"/>. For AC circuits the values typically cited for current (<m>I</m>)
        and voltage (<m>E</m>) are in fact therms values, and not the peak values. These rms values
        are each about 71 % of the peak values. For 120 volt, 60 Hz power, the rms values are +120
        volts and -120 volts, while the peak values are +170 volts and -170 volts, yielding a
          <term>peak-to-peak voltage</term> of 340 volts.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <figure xml:id="fig_24_1_png">
                  <caption>60 Hz AC voltage sine wave</caption>
                  <image source="pics/sname/24-1.png" width="50%"/>
               </figure>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>In <xref ref="fig_24_2_png"/>, note that the voltage reaches its peak value before the
        current reaches its peak, so that the current is said to be <term>lagging</term>. If the
        current were to reach its peak first we would say that it is <term>leading</term>. The
        degree of lagging or leading is dependent on the circuit components, and their response to
        the cyclic fluctuations of the alternating current and voltage. Note that it takes 360
        degrees for a sine wave to complete its cycle, enabling the abscissa in <xref ref="fig_24_2_png"/> to be given in degrees as shown. The difference between corresponding
        points on the two sine waves for voltage and current, measured in degrees, is called the
          <term>phase shift</term>.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Power is the product of current and voltage, but it can be seen in <xref ref="fig_24_2_png"/> that whenever there is a phase shift, this product will never reach the high values that
        it would reach if the current and voltage acted in unison. For example, at 90 degrees the
        voltage is 100% of its peak value but the current is at only 60% of its peak value, so that
        the instantaneous power is only 60% of what it would be if current and voltage reached their
        peak values together at 90 degrees. To account for the lower power caused by a phase shift,
        the power factor (pf) is defined as follows: <me> pf = \frac{\text{active
          power}}{\text{apparent power}}</me>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <figure xml:id="fig_24_2_png">
                  <caption>Alternating current with lagging voltage</caption>
                  <image source="pics/sname/24-2.png" width="50%"/>
               </figure>
            </item>
            <item>
               <figure xml:id="fig_24_3_png">
                  <caption>AC voltage - peak and rms values</caption>
                  <image source="pics/sname/24-3.png" width="50%"/>
               </figure>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The <term>apparent power</term> is simply the product of the rms voltage (<m>E</m>) and the
        rms current (<m>I</m>), and is expressed in volt-amperes (VA) or kilovolt-amperes (kVA). The
          <term>active power</term>, which is the <term>real power</term>, is expressed In watts or
        kilowatts. <md>
                     <mrow>\text{apparent power in kVA}= EI</mrow>
                     <mrow>\text{active (real) power in kW} = pf \times EI</mrow>
                  </md>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>If there is no phase shift, then the voltage and current follow sine curves that are
        exactly in step. In these cases the voltage and current are said to be <term>in
        phase</term>, the active power is equal to the apparent power, and the power factor is one.
        This condition is the exception, rather than the rule. More often, the power factor is less
        than one because the voltage and current cycles do not coincide, that is they are <term>out
          of phase</term>, and the active power (kW) is therefore less than the product of volts and
        amperes. The significance of the power factor, therefore, is that only at a power factor of
        one, where the voltage and current are in phase, will the real power be equal to the product
        of the volts and amperes. Usually the voltage and current are out of phase, the power factor
        is less than one, and the active power is less than the product of volts and amperes.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>To appreciate the significance of having voltage and current out of phase, it should be
        noted that what is required from an electric circuit Is usually a certain amount of real
        power, such as might be needed to drive a motor. If the power factor is less than one, and
        if the voltage is fixed, then for the required real power a higher current is necessary than
        if the voltage and current were in phase. Recall that whenever there is a current in a
        conductor there is also a <q>loss</q>, and that this <q>loss</q> is proportional to the
        square of the current. For example, in a circuit supplying a motor with AC power, if the
        power factor is 0.8, then the current must rise to 125% of what would be required for the
        same power if the power factor were one, while the <q>loss</q> in the conductors rises to
        156% (125% squared). Viewed another way, all of the current contributes to wasteful heat
        generation, even when only a portion of the current contributes to the real power.</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section" xml:id="Basic_electric_circuits">
         <Title>Basic electric circuits</Title>
         <item>
            <p>Basic electric circuits are either <term>series</term> circuits or <term>parallel</term>
      circuits.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>In a series circuit, the components are connected in succession, so that the total line
      current must pass through each of the components in turn, as in <xref ref="fig_24_4_png"/>.
      Therefore, for the resistors in this circuit: <me>I = I_1 = I_2 = I_3</me>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure xml:id="fig_24_4_png">
               <caption>Series Circuit</caption>
               <image source="pics/sname/24-4.png" width="50%"/>
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>The total voltage drop across these resistors is the sum of the voltage drops across each of
      the resistors: <me> V = V_1 + V_2 + V_3</me>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Recalling Ohm's Law (<m>I=V/R</m> or <m>V=IR</m>), the <term>equivalent resistance</term>
        (<m>R_e</m>) of the series circuit is:<me> R_e = R_1 + R_2 + R_3</me>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>And the voltage drop across each of the resistors is equal to the line current times that
      resistance of that resistor:<md>
                  <mrow>V_1 \amp= I_1 R_1 \amp V_2 \amp= I_2 R_2 \amp V_3 \amp= I_3 R_3 \amp</mrow>
               </md>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>In a parallel circuit, the components are connected in branches, which permit the current to
      divide and flow through two or more independent parallel paths, as shown in <xref ref="fig_24_5_png"/> on the left. Therefore, each of the three resistors has the full line
      voltage across it: <me> V = V_1 = V_2 = V_3</me>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>At the same time, the total line current is the sum of the three branch current flows: <me> I
        = I_1 + I_2 + I_3</me>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>The equivalent resistance of a parallel circuit is the value of a single resistor that would
      pass the same line current as the group of resistors in the parallel circuit, as shown on the
      right in <xref ref="fig_24_5_png"/>. This equivalent resistance can be calculated for the
      parallel circuit of the figure using Ohm's Law, which yields: <me> R_e = \frac{1}{1/R_1 +
        1/R_2 + 1/R_3}</me>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure xml:id="fig_24_5_png">
               <caption>Parallel circuit and circuit with equivalent resistance</caption>
               <image source="pics/sname/24-5.png" width="85%"/>
            </figure>
         </item>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section" xml:id="Electric_components_and_instruments">
         <Title>Electric components and instruments</Title>
         <item>
            <p>A short list of electric components and instruments most likely to be of interest to marine
      engineers appears in this section.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <term>Voltmeters</term> are used to measure the strength of the electromotive force or
      potential between two points. </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>At the heart of a voltmeter is a pivoted movement, surrounded by a coil. The movement is
      attached to the pointer, and turns in response to the magnetic field produced by the small
      current that flows in the coil when a voltage is applied across the meter terminals.
      Voltmeters are connected in parallel to the component for which the voltage drop is desired as
      shown in <xref ref="fig_24_6_png"/>. Voltmeters must have high ·internal resistance so that
      the current they draw is negligible. In low-voltage electronic circuits, ordinary voltmeters
      may draw too much current to permit their use.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure xml:id="fig_24_6_png">
               <caption>Voltmeter</caption>
               <image source="pics/sname/24-6.png" width="50%"/>
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <term>Voltage testers</term> are used where it is necessary to know only whether there is
      full voltage or no voltage.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <term>Ammeters</term> are used to measure current. The basic movement of an ammeter is
      similar to that of a voltmeter, but the coil of the meter is wired in parallel with a
      low-resistance resistor called a shunt. The movement then responds to the voltage drop
      associated with a particular current in the shunt. The scale is graduated in appropriate units
      such as milliamperes (1 ma is one-thousandth of an amp) or amps, depending on the shunt.
      Ammeters are connected in a series with the conductor in which the current flow is to be
      measured. A basic ammeter with its integral shunt is shown in <xref ref="fig_24_7_png"/>.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure xml:id="fig_24_7_png">
               <caption>Ammeteter</caption>
               <image source="pics/sname/24-7.png" width="50%"/>
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <term>Clamp-on ammeters</term> are hand-held instruments used with AC circuits. A plier-like
      pick-up coil is closed around the conductor in which current is to be measured, and the
      movement responds to current induced in the pick-up coil by the changing magnetic field in the
      conductor.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <term>Ohmmeters</term> are used to measure resistance. An ohmmeter consists of a simple meter
      movement connected in series with a battery. When the ohmmeter is connected in series with the
      component or circuit to be tested, the battery, which acts as a constant-voltage source,
      supplies current to develop a voltage drop across the test device. The movement is calibrated
      to read in ohms. Ohmmeters must never be used on energized circuits.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>A <term>megger</term> is a special ohmmeter used for testing electric insulation. The voltage
      source is a hand-cranked DC generator. Meggers are used only when equipment is secured and
      isolated from the power source. After connection to the selected insulated component, the high
      voltage from the generator is applied momentarily, while the meter measures the current flow
      through the insulation. Meggers are calibrated in megohms.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>A <term>multimeter</term> is an instrument containing one movement that can be connected by a
      selector switch to a variety of shunts to serve as an ammeter, or to special resistors to
      serve as a voltmeter, or to a small dry cell battery for use as an oh meter.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <term>Wattmeters</term> are used to measure electric power. Since electric power is the
      product of current and voltage, a wattmeter will have four connections, two for measuring
      current and two for measuring voltage.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Clamp-on wattmeters are similar to clamp-on ammeters in having a plier-like pick-up coil to
      measure current, but they also have two or three leads for connection to the power leads, in
      order to simultaneously measure voltage.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <term>Watt-hour meters</term> are used to measure the amount of energy consumed over time.
      Watt-hour meters must not only measure power (current and voltage) but must also have device
      for measuring the time interval involved.</p>
         </item>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section" xml:id="Alternators_and_generators">
         <Title>Alternators and generators</Title>
         <folder ptx="introduction">
            <Title>introduction</Title>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <term>Generators</term> are machines for producing DC electric power, while alternators are
        machines that produce AC power. It is common to refer to alternators as generators. Aboard
        ship generators and alternators are rotating machines driven by engines or turbines, serving
        as the normal source of electricity, and on larger vessels, for standby and emergency
        electric power as well.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>When a conductor is passed through a magnetic field, or when a magnetic field is passed
        over a conductor, an <term>electromotive force</term> or <term>impressed voltage</term> is
        induced in the conductor. If the conductor is part of a complete circuit, the current that
        will then flow is called an <term>induced current</term>. The linkage of relative motion
        between a magnetic field and a conductor, and the resulting impressed voltage and induced
        current, is the principle behind generators and alternators. In a generator, conductors are
        arranged on the rotor, driven through a stationary magnetic field by a prime mover, with the
        induced current collected from the rotor for delivery to the load. In most alternators, the
        conductors are stationary, and surround a rotating magnetic field: current is induced in the
        stationary conductors as they are swept by the magnetic field.</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection">
            <Title>Single-phase alternators</Title>
            <item>
               <p>In the simple alternator of <xref ref="fig_24_8_png"/> the engine or turbine spins a magnet
        (on the rotor}, with north and south <term>poles</term>, which is surrounded by a coil of
        stationary conductors (the winding on the <term>stator</term>). The magnitude of the
        impressed voltage will depend on the strength of the magnetic field, denoted as
          <term>magnetic flux</term>, and the speed at which the conductors are swept or "cut" by
        the magnetic flux.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <figure xml:id="fig_24_8_png">
                  <caption>Single-phase alternator with two-pole rotor</caption>
                  <image source="pics/sname/24-8.png" width="50%"/>
               </figure>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Because of the rotation of the magnetic poles the impressed voltage is not constant, but
        varies in magnitude and direction cyclically, as shown in <xref ref="fig_24_1_png"/>. The
        flux cutting the right side of the conductor is that associated with a south pole, but when
        the magnet rotates 180 degrees the conductor is being cut by the flux associated with the
        north pole, reversing the direction or <term>polarity</term> of the voltage. When the magnet
        is vertical no flux cuts the conductors and therefore no voltage is impressed. The result is
        a voltage curve with the shape of a sine wave, as shown in <xref ref="fig_24_1_png"/>. Since
        this alternator generates voltage that is described by a single sine wave It is a
          <term>single-phase</term> alternator.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>If the two-pole rotor (one north and one south pole) of <xref ref="fig_24_8_png"/> is
        rotated at 3600 rpm the current will have a frequency of 3600 cycles per minute or 60 cycles
        per second. If the rotor were a four-pole magnet as in <xref ref="fig_24_9_png"/>, then in
        each revolution of the rotor the conductors in the winding will be cut by the magnetic field
        twice as frequently. Turning the rotor at 1800 rpm would then produce the same 60 Hz sine
        wave. The frequency of the voltage generated by an alternator can be expressed as: <me>f =
          \frac{120 \times N}{2 \times 60}</me>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>where <m>f</m> is the frequency in Hz and <m>N</m> is the total number of poles.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <figure xml:id="fig_24_9_png">
                  <caption>Four-pole rotor for an alternator</caption>
                  <image source="pics/sname/24-9.png" width="60%"/>
               </figure>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection">
            <Title>Three-phase alternators</Title>
            <item>
               <p>If a two-pole generator were fitted with three sets of windings on the stator, as in <xref ref="fig_24_10_png"/>, a three-phase alternator results. The windings are positioned 120
        degrees apart and are not connected to each other. As the poles of the field rotate a
        sinusoidal voltage is induced in turn in each winding, 120 degrees out of phase with the
        voltage produced in the adjacent windings. Each winding has one end connected to a common
        ground, and the voltages that result, <m>V_1</m>, <m>V_2</m>, and <m>V_3</m>, measured
        relative to ground, are shown in <xref ref="fig_24_11_png"/>.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <figure xml:id="fig_24_11_png">
                  <caption>Three-phase voltage</caption>
                  <image source="pics/sname/24-11.png" width="75%"/>
               </figure>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection">
            <Title>Field and excitation</Title>
            <item>
               <p>In most generators the magnet that provides the field is an electromagnet, comprised of a
        steel core wound with coils of wire that form the <term>field windings</term>, as in <xref ref="fig_24_12_png"/>. The <term>field</term> is energized by the <term>excitation
          current</term> that flows through these field windings. To maintain the polarity of the
        field, the excitation must be direct current. <xref ref="fig_24_12_png"/> shows how copper
          <term>slip rings</term> mounted on the rotor are used with stationary carbon
          <term>brushes</term> to provide the electrical connection from the excitation source to
        the field windings. The brushes are pressed against the slip rings by springs, and are
        replaced as they wear.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <figure xml:id="fig_24_12_png">
                  <caption>Rotating field for two-pole alternator, showing slip rings</caption>
                  <image source="pics/sname/24-12.png" width="75%"/>
               </figure>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Most generators are <term>self-excited</term>, meaning that the excitation current is
        derived from the power produced by the generator. Starting of a self-excited generator makes
        use of the residual permanent magnetism of the field core. Once the generator starts
        rotating, the residual permanent magnetism induces current to begin to excite the field
        coils, and the resulting magnetic flux builds up to the desired level.</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection">
            <Title>Direct-current generators</Title>
            <item>
               <p>Since any generator with a rotating element will naturally produce an alternating voltage,
        it is necessary, in a DC generator, to continually convert this alternating voltage into a
        direct voltage. In traditional DC generators the construction of the machine is reversed
        relative to the alternators discussed above, so that the magnetic field is stationary, while
        the windings rotate, as in <xref ref="fig_24_13_png"/>. The rotor is then called the
          <term>armature</term>, and is fitted with a rotating switching device called a
          <term>commutator</term>, which does the AC to DC conversion. The voltage produced in the
        windings of the armature is sinusoidal, as it is in an alternator. If this voltage were
        taken out of the rotor by slip rings and brushes, as in <xref ref="fig_24_12_png"/>,
        single-phase AC would be delivered to the generator terminals. The commutator is essentially
        a single slip ring divided into separate segments called <term>commutator bars</term>. Each
        terminal of the armature winding is connected to one commutator bar. As the armature
        rotates, the winding terminal beneath each brush switches half way through every revolution,
        simultaneously with the change in polarity of the voltage in the winding. The polarity of
        one brush and its connected generator terminal is thus always positive, while the other
        brush and generator terminal is always negative.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <figure xml:id="fig_24_13_png">
                  <caption>Two-pole DC generator with commutator</caption>
                  <image source="pics/sname/24-13.png" width="75%"/>
               </figure>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The DC voltage produced by a generator with a single armature winding and a two-bar
        commutator fluctuates as shown in the upper plot of <xref ref="fig_24_14_png"/>. To obtain a
        more constant voltage more windings would be added to the armature, with each winding
        connected to a pair of diametrically-opposed commutator bars, to yield an output voltage
        curve as shown in the lower plot of <xref ref="fig_24_14_png"/>. The more windings there are
        on the armature, the steadier will be the resulting terminal voltage of the generator. Large
        DC generators have dozens of armature windings and commutator bars.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <figure xml:id="fig_24_14_png">
                  <caption>Voltage delivered by a DC generator with, at top, a single winding and a
          two-segment commutator, and, at bottom, three evenly-spaced windings and as six-bar
          commutator.</caption>
                  <image source="pics/sname/24-14.png" width="60%"/>
               </figure>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>A commutator is only one way to achieve the continual switching necessary to convert AC to
        DC; electronic devices called <term>rectifiers</term> are also used. Modern rectifiers are
        built around solid-state <term>diodes</term>. A diode has low resistance to current flow in
        one direction and very high resistance to current flow in the other direction. <xref ref="fig_24_15_png"/> depicts a rectifier circuit. By appropriately connecting rectifiers
        to the stator windings of an alternator, DC can be provided without the maintenance problems
        associated with brushes and commutators. Alternators can be used in automobiles, where the
        power is distributed as DC, because they are fitted with rectifiers.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <figure xml:id="fig_24_15_png">
                  <caption>Rectifier</caption>
                  <image source="pics/sname/24-15.png" width="50%"/>
               </figure>
            </item>
         </folder>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section" xml:id="Electric_motors">
         <Title>Electric motors</Title>
         <folder ptx="introduction">
            <Title>introduction</Title>
            <item>
               <p>An electric motor has a role opposite to that of a generator, in that a motor draws
        electric power and converts it to mechanical power. Most shipboard motors are AC, because
        they are smaller and less costly than DC motors of similar power output. DC motors are used
        only rarely on modern ships. <term>Universal motors</term> operate on either AC or DC.</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection">
            <Title>Alternating current motors</Title>
            <item>
               <p>In concept and construction, a three-phase AC motor is very similar to a three-phase
        alternator, as shown in <xref ref="fig_24_10_png"/>. When three-phase AC current (the line
        current) is applied to the stator windings of the motor, with one phase connected to each
        winding, the current will produce a magnetic field around each winding that varies in
        magnitude and direction in a sinusoidal pattern. The magnetic field produced by each winding
        interacts with that of the adjoining windings to produce a net magnetic field that revolves
        around the stator. If a compass needle were placed in the center of the stator it would
        rotate at a speed coinciding with the frequency of the applied current, since the compass
        needle is a two-pole magnet. The direction of rotation of the field will depend on the order
        in which the windings are connected to receive the line current: if two of the three line
        connections are interchanged at the motor terminals, the direction in which the magnetic
        field produced by the stator windings will reverse, as will the compass needle.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The stator windings of the three-phase machine in <xref ref="fig_24_10_png"/> are spaced at
        120-degree intervals, so that the field produced by these stator windings rotates once per
        cycle of the applied current, a speed <m>n_s</m>called the <term>synchronous speed</term>.
        This stator is said to have two poles, and the corresponding synchronous speed can be
        calculated from the following relation: <me>n_s = \frac{120 f}{P}</me>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <figure xml:id="fig_24_10_png">
                  <caption>Three-phase alternator</caption>
                  <image source="pics/sname/24-10.png" width="75%"/>
               </figure>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>where <m>P</m> is the number of poles on the stator and <m>f</m> is the line frequency. A
        two-pole stator supplied with 60 Hz line current would have a synchronous speed of 3600 rpm.
        In this example, the magnetic field produced by the stator and the compass needle would both
        rotate at this speed.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Additional windings can be fitted to the stator for each phase. Each additional winding per
        phase provides an additional pair of poles. For example, the stator could be arranged with
        nine windings, with every third winding connected to the same phase, so that there are three
        windings per phase. Since each set of windings provides one pair of poles this would be a
        6-pole motor. The synchronous speed of a 6-pole motor, when supplied with 60 Hz line
        current, is 1200 rpm.</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection">
            <Title>Synchronous motors</Title>
            <item>
               <p>If we replace the compass needle in the above example with a more powerful magnet, the
        magnetic field produced by this magnet would lock onto the rotating magnetic field produced
        by the stator windings. The rotor can be a strong permanent magnet or an electromagnet
        supplied (excited) by a DC source. This type of AC motor is called a <term>synchronous
          motor</term> and is characterized by the fact that the rotor rotates at the same speed as
        the magnetic field produced by the stator windings, the synchronous speed. Synchronous
        motors range in size from small motors for electric clocks fitted with permanent-magnet
        rotors, to very large propulsion motors, developing 70,000 HP or more, with electromagnetic
        rotors.</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection">
            <Title>Induction motors</Title>
            <item>
               <p>A more common type of AC motor, widely used for driving pumps and fans, is the
          <term>induction motor</term>. In most induction motors the rotor is built up of laminated
        steel plates, into which are inserted a number of conductor <term>bars</term>, connected at
        the ends by <term>end-connecting rings</term> as shown in <xref ref="fig_24_16_png"/>.
        Without the core, the conductor bars and end-connecting rings would form a rotating
        cage-like structure, for which reason this type of motor is often called a
          <term>squirrel-cage induction motor</term>.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <figure xml:id="fig_24_16_png">
                  <caption>Squirrel-cage rotor for AC induction motor</caption>
                  <image source="pics/sname/24-16.png" width="75%"/>
               </figure>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>If a squirrel-cage rotor is placed in the rotating magnetic field of an AC-motor stator,
        but is locked to prevent its rotation, then as the rotating magnetic field, produced by the
        stator, crosses the conductor bars it will induce a voltage in these bars, and therefore a
        current will circulate through the rotor, since the bars are connected together to form a
        complete circuit. The current in the bars of the rotor produces a magnetic field surrounding
        the bars, which causes the rotor to act as if it were a permanent magnet or electromagnet.
        If the rotor were then released it would rotate as any magnet would, and will accelerate
        towards the synchronous speed of the stator field. However, it will never reach synchronous
        speed because, if it did, the conductor bars of the rotor would no longer be crossed by the
        rotating magnetic field of the stator and no induced rotor current or rotor magnetism would
        result. Therefore, induction-motor rotors always run at a speed slightly less than the
        synchronous speed in order to induce a voltage and current in the rotor conductor bars. The
        difference from synchronous speed is called the <term>slip</term> and is defined as follows:
          <me> \text{\% slip} = \frac{\text{synchronous speed} - \text{actual rotor
          speed}}{\text{synchronous speed}} \times 100\%</me>
               </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>As the torque on an induction motor increases, the rotor must slow down (slip must
        increase) so that sufficient current is induced in the conductor bars of the rotor to
        develop an induced magnetism strong enough to develop the necessary torque. However, it is
        important to note that the slip is not much more than five percent even at high torque, so
        that induction motors are almost constant-speed machines when supplied with
        constant-frequency line power.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>As with synchronous motors, induction~motor stators can have multiple pairs of stator poles
        for different speed requirements, and that they can easily be reversed by interchanging two
        of the three line connections.</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection">
            <Title>Single-phase motors</Title>
            <item>
               <p>Although most large motors aboard ship are supplied with three-phase power, smaller motors,
        such as those driving appliances, must operate from single-phase circuits.
          <term>Single-phase motors</term> are most often arranged with two sets of stator windings,
        with the second set supplied from the line connections through a <term>capacitor</term>. The
        capacitor imposes a phase shift on the line current reaching these windings, to make it look
        like two-phase AC current. The stator is thus able to develop a rotating magnetic field to
        drive a rotor.</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection">
            <Title>DC motors</Title>
            <item>
               <p>In construction, DC motors are similar to DC generators. The traditional advantage that DC
        motors have had over AC motors is that, unlike AC motors, their speed can be easily
        controlled over a wide range by a <term>rheostat</term>. A rheostat is an easily adjusted
        variable resistor that can be connected in series with the motor field windings to control
        field current and, therefore, motor speed. However, solid-state electronic controls like
        variable frequency converters are now available, allowing AC motors to be operated with
        variable speed. Consequently, few DC motors are found aboard modern ships.</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section" xml:id="Transformers">
         <Title>Transformers</Title>
         <item>
            <p>An advantage of AC power is that <term>transformers</term> can be used to easily and
      efficiently change the magnitude of the voltage to best meet requirements. Transformers are
      simple, have no moving components, and are easily maintained.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Transformers convert AC power from one voltage to another by taking advantage of the varying
      magnetic field developed by an AC current and the fact that this fluctuating magnetic field
      can induce a voltage in a second conductor. Simple transformers consist of a <term>primary
        winding</term> wound around a laminated-steel core, which is also wound with a second
      winding, the <term>secondary winding</term>. Typically the core and windings are arranged as
      shown in <xref ref="fig_24_17_png"/>. If the secondary winding has more coils or
        <term>turns</term> than the primary winding, the secondary voltage will be higher than the
      primary voltage and the transformer is referred to as a <term>step-up</term> transformer.
      Conversely, if the secondary winding has fewer turns than the primary winding the secondary
      voltage will be less than the primary voltage, and the transformer is a <term>step-down</term>
      transformer. The relationships between transformer voltages and currents are as follows, where
        <m>n</m> is the number of turns in each winding: <md>
                  <mrow>V_1 n_2 \amp= V_2 n_1</mrow>
                  <mrow>I_1 n_1 \amp = I_2 n_2</mrow>
               </md>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure xml:id="fig_24_17_png">
               <caption>Transformer</caption>
               <image source="pics/sname/24-17.png" width="85%"/>
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Transformer cores are made of steel laminates which are electrically insulated from each
      other in order to reduce <term>hysteresis</term> losses in the magnetic core. Overall
      transformer efficiencies are very high, 98 to 99%.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Auto-transformers have a core with only one winding, arranged with one or more
        <term>taps</term>, as shown in <xref ref="fig_24_18_png"/>. The taps are used to take off
      secondary voltages of lower magnitude than the full secondary voltage. The magnitude of the
      tapped voltage is dependent on the relative number of turns in the respective sections of the
      transformer.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure xml:id="fig_24_18_png">
               <caption>Autotransformer</caption>
               <image source="pics/sname/24-18.png" width="75%"/>
            </figure>
         </item>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section" xml:id="Motor_starters">
         <Title>Motor starters</Title>
         <folder ptx="subsection">
            <Title>Motor starting current</Title>
            <item>
               <p>When the rotor of an AC motor rotates, the magnetic field surrounding the rotor interacts
        with the stationary windings to induce a voltage in the windings. This induced voltage is
        opposite in polarity to the line voltage, and therefore it actually counteracts the effect
        of the line voltage at the motor terminals. An analogous effect occurs in DC motor
        armatures, where the induced voltage is called the <term>counter</term> or <term>back
          electromotive force</term>, or <term>back emf</term>. The induced voltage or back emf
        limits the current flow through the windings.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Since a motor rotor needs to be rotating to generate induced voltage or back emf, a motor
        which is just being started, whose rotor has not yet begun to turn, will have no such
        induced voltage or back emf. At starting, therefore, current will be limited only by the
        impedance and resistance of the motor windings. As a result, when full line voltage is
        applied to a motor at starting the <term>motor starting current</term> will be many times
        greater than the full-power running current. As the rotor accelerates, the induced voltage
        or back emf increases, and the current in the line and motor windings falls to normal
        values.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>High starting currents have two negative effects, which affect large motors in particular.
        First, the high current in the windings can generate enough heat to damage the motor,
        especially if the driven load accelerates slowly. Second, the very high starting current can
        draw down line voltage sufficiently to cause lights to dim and other equipment being
        supplied from the same line to malfunction. For these reasons all DC motors and large AC
        motors are started with reduced voltage applied to the motor terminals by a <term>motor
          starter.</term>
               </p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection">
            <Title>Motor starters</Title>
            <item>
               <p>AC motor starters are of two general types, across-the-line starters and reduced-voltage
        starters.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Across-the-line starters are commonly used for small and medium-power AC motors where the
        line capacity is sufficient to prevent objectionable voltage drops upon starting, and where
        the driven loads allow the motor to accelerate quickly. As the name implies, this type of
        starter simply closes the necessary contacts to apply full line voltage to the motor
        terminals. <xref ref="fig_24_19_png"/> depicts a simple across-the-line starter. When the
        run button is depressed the magnetic-hold solenoid is energized to close the <m>L_1</m>,
          <m>L_2</m>, and <m>L_3</m> contacts, sending current to the motor. </p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <figure xml:id="fig_24_19_png">
                  <caption>Across-the-line starter</caption>
                  <image source="pics/sname/24-19.png" width="75%"/>
               </figure>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>Reduced-voltage starters are used for larger motors or where the supply lines are not large
        enough to handle the full starting current. Reduced-voltage AC starters use
        auto-transformers with one or more taps to obtain the necessary reduced voltage. A simple
        reduced-voltage starter is shown in <xref ref="fig_24_20_png"/>. Depressing the start button
        initially supplies current to the motor at reduced voltage, but also starts a timer. As the
        motor accelerates, the timer bypasses the autotransformer to apply full line voltage to the
        motor terminals.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <figure xml:id="fig_24_20_png">
                  <caption>Reduced-voltage starter</caption>
                  <image source="pics/sname/24-20.png" width="80%"/>
               </figure>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The simple starters shown in these figures include overload trips, but do not include other
        protective devices that are normal features of actual starters.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>DC motor starters use resistors to limit the initial starting current. As the motor
        accelerates the resistors are automatically removed from the circuit.</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section" xml:id="Batteries_and_fuel_cells">
         <Title>Batteries and fuel cells</Title>
         <folder ptx="introduction">
            <Title>introduction</Title>
            <item>
               <p>Batteries and fuel cells are electro-chemical, direct-current power supplies. Batteries
        provide power for finite periods of time before they are replaced or recharged. Aboard ship,
        batteries are used as power supplies for portable equipment, as temporary emergency-power
        sources, and for starting small auxiliary engines. On the other hand, fuel cells are
        continuous power sources, and while not yet in use aboard ship, they are considered a
        likely, near-future alternative to generators.</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection">
            <Title>Batteries</Title>
            <item>
               <p>The chemical energy stored in a battery is finite in quantity, and is measured as its
          <term>ampere-hour capacity</term>. As electric power is drawn from the battery, the
        chemical energy is depleted until the cells are discharged. Batteries are classified as
        either <term>primary</term> or <term>secondary</term> depending on whether they are
        discarded after discharge or are rechargeable, respectively. Most batteries used aboard ship
        are rechargeable after use.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>
                  <term>Dry cells</term> contain an <term>electrolyte</term> in a solid or semi-solid state,
        while <term>wet cells</term> contain a liquid electrolyte. Dry cells are commonly used for
        low-power purposes, as in flashlights and other portable equipment. and as back-up supplies
        for computers. Large, wet-cell <term>storage batteries</term> are used where higher power is
        required, such as for starting small auxiliary engines, and as short-term power supplies for
        emergency lighting and control circuits.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
               <p>The two most common types of wet-cell storage batteries are the <term>lead-acid</term> and
        the <term>nickel-cadmium alkali (Nicad)</term> types. Generally, a battery is made up of a
        number of cells connected in series, with each cell delivering 1.5 volts or less. The state
        of charge of a battery is determined differently for each type. For lead•acid batteries the
        charge is determined by measuring the density of the electrolyte with a hydrometer, while
        the charge of the Nicad batteries is determined by measuring the cell voltage.</p>
            </item>
         </folder>
         <folder ptx="subsection">
            <Title>Fuel cells</Title>
            <item>
               <p>Fuel cells are similar to·batteries but supply power continuously because the electrolyte
        is continuously rejuvenated. This rejuvenation is achieved by continuously adding hydrogen
        and oxygen to the electrolyte. Fuel cells operating on pure hydrogen have been used in space
        vehicles for years, but advancing technology will allow fuel cell systems to operate on less
        expensive, readily available hydrocarbon fuels from which the hydrogen can be separated.
        Fuel-cell systems have the potential to achieve efficiencies higher than those based on
        engine-driven generators. </p>
            </item>
         </folder>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section" xml:id="Shipboard_electric_systems">
         <Title>Shipboard electric systems</Title>
         <item>
            <p>Most American ships use 60 Hz AC supplied at 480 volts. For large shipboard electric plants,
      where the ship's generating capacity is above 2500 kW, it is often more economical to supply
      the power at 2400 or 4160 volts. 50 Hz is common on foreign ships. Some naval vessels use 400
      Hz for special applications.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Regulations normally require that a ship's electric-generating plant must be capable of
      supplying the design electric load with one generator shut down. Most ships therefore have two
      or three <term>ship's-service generators</term>. The ship's-service generators are connected
      to the <term> main switchboard</term>, which includes generator panels and <term>distribution
        switchboards</term>, connected by large conductors called bus bars. From the distribution
      switchboards the power is passed through <term>feeders</term> to other switchboards called
        <term>load centers</term>, <term>group-control centers</term>, and <term>power
      panels</term>. These switchboards house <term>circuit breakers</term> and control equipment
      known collectively as <term>switchgear</term>. <xref ref="fig_24_21_png"/> is a <term>one-line
        diagram</term>, which shows the electric <term>distribution system</term> for a typical
      merchant ship. An emergency switchboard is used to supply electric power to vital loads and is
      normally supplied with power from the main switchboard. In the event of a complete loss of
      electric power (a <term>black-out</term>) the emergency switchboard is isolated from the main
      switchboard, and supplied with power from the <term>emergency generator</term>. The emergency
      generator is required to be located outside of the engine room and above the ship's margin
      line (3 inches or 75 mm above the bulkhead deck, sometimes referred to the upper deck).</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure xml:id="fig_24_21_png">
               <caption>One-line diagram of electrical distribution system</caption>
               <image source="pics/sname/24-21.png" width="100%"/>
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>Most shipboard motors driving pumps, compressors, and blowers are 460 volt, three-phase
      motors. The motors are assumed to receive power at 460 volts, although the power is generated
      at 480 volts, because of the <term>voltage drop</term> associated with the line losses in the
      conductors and switchgear. When power levels are high, high voltages (2400 or 4160 volts) are
      preferable for transmission since, for a given power, the current decreases proportionally as
      the voltage goes up (power is proportional to the product of voltage and current). Low
      currents allow smaller conductors and cause lower line losses (line losses are proportional to
      the square of the current).</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>For safety reasons and for commonality with shore-side equipment, the power used for lighting
      circuits, and for general distribution to accommodation and work areas of a ship, is reduced
      to a lower voltage by transformers. On American ships 120 volt, single-phase power is normal
      for these purposes, but 220 volt, single-phase power is common on other vessels. Specialized
      equipment aboard ship, such as control systems and battery chargers, usually use even lower
      voltages, with 24 volts being a typical value.</p>
         </item>
      </folder>
      <folder ptx="section" xml:id="Electric_propulsion">
         <Title>Electric propulsion</Title>
         <item>
            <p>Electric drives for ship propulsion have been used for over 100 years, employing generators
      driven by steam turbines, diesel engines, or gas turbines to power the <term>propulsion
        motor</term>(s) on the propeller shaft(s). ln comparison to geared drive, electric drive is
      more expensive to install, heavier, and less efficient. Electric drive is therefore normally
      used only where these disadvantages are outweighed by the advantages, which include excellent
      control of propeller speed and direction, as well as the flexibility of locating the
      generators and their prime movers in different spaces than the propulsion motors. A further
      advantage is that the power output from any number of generators can be combined to drive one
      or more propulsion motors.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>When ship's service power as well as propulsion power is derived from the same generators,
      the ship is said to have an <term>integrated</term> power plant.</p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>
               <xref ref="fig_24_22_png"/> shows a modern electric-propulsion system using AC/AC
      variable-frequency drive. In this system the mechanical prime mover drives an AC generator at
      constant speed, enabling ship's services to be supplied at constant frequency. For full speed
      of the ship, the maximum rpm of the propeller can be achieved without the frequency converter,
      based on the ratio of numbers of poles: <me>\text{rpm}_{\text{motor}} =
        \text{rpm}_{\text{alternator}} \left(\frac{N_a}{N_m}\right)</me>
            </p>
         </item>
         <item>
            <figure xml:id="fig_24_22_png">
               <caption>Electric drive with multiple prime movers and frequency converter</caption>
               <image source="pics/sname/24-22.png" width="85%"/>
            </figure>
         </item>
         <item>
            <p>where <m>N_a</m> and <m>N_m</m> are the numbers of poles in the alternator and propulsion
      motor respectively. As an example, if the prime mover is a gas turbine running at 3600 rpm,
      driving a two-pole alternator, and the propulsion motor is a 60-pole synchronous motor
      directly connected to the propeller shaft, the propeller will turn at 120 rpm. (If an
      induction motor is used, the propeller rpm will be slightly lower.) For maneuvering, lower
      propeller rpm is achieved without changing the generator speed by using the frequency
      converter to reduce the frequency of the power to the propulsion motor. Reversing of the
      propulsion motor is easily accomplished by switching two of the three leads supplying the
      motor. </p>
         </item>
      </folder>
   </folder>
</folder>
