<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- intermediate copy. Process with scriv2ptx.xslt -->
<pretext xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<xi:include href="docinfo.ptx"/>
<book >
<title>Introduction to Marine Engineering</title>
<chapter xml:id="engineering-measurement"> 
<title>Engineering Measurement</title>
<objectives>
<ul><li>Understand the units of measurement for length, mass, time, area, volume, speed, temperature, pressure, torque, power, and speed</li>
<li>Understand conversions from U.S to metric and metric to U.S.</li>
<li>Understand Nautical Mile definition</li>
<li>Be able to calculate conversions</li>
<li>Identify and draw standard measurement symbols</li>
<li>Understand basic measuring instruments</li>
<li>Understand accuracy, precision, tolerance, calibration</li>
</ul>
</objectives>
<introduction>
<p>Measurement is the process of associating numbers with quantities. Units of measurement establish a common language for engineers to communicate and quantify various physical quantities. There are two basic standard units of measurement systems that are used worldwide, the U.S. Standard Measurement System and the Metric System.</p>
<p>In the world of engineering, measurement is fundamental. Accurate measurements are crucial for designing, constructing, and evaluating systems. Engineers rely on standardized units and principles of measurement to ensure consistency and precision in their work.</p>
<p>This chapter provides an overview of the categories and units of measurement used in engineering systems, covering both the metric and US standard systems as well as nautical measurement. An overview of basic instruments used for making measurements will be discussed along with the principles of measurement <term>including</term> accuracy, efficiency, percent error and deviation.</p>
<p>As you study this chapter, you will encounter new terms and definitions for you to learn. At the end of the chapter, you will find example problems. Be sure to take the time to practice with these problems. They will help prepare you to apply these concepts.</p></introduction>

<section xml:id=""><title>Units of Measurement</title>
<objectives>
<ul><li>Length</li>
<li>Mass</li>
<li>Time</li>
<li>Area</li>
<li>Volume</li>
<li>Temperature</li>
<li>Pressure</li>
<li>Torque</li>
<li>Power</li>
<li>Speed</li></ul>
</objectives>
<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Length</title>
<subsubsection  xml:id="" ><title>A Brief History</title>


<p>The way base units of length have been determined has changed greatly over time. Long ago, the base for reference was the human body. For example, the cubit was a unit that indicated the length from the elbow to the fingertips.</p>
<p>Length units based on the human body were used for thousands of years. The Roman mile (In Latin <foreign>mille passus </foreign>, which means <q>thousand paces</q>) consisted of a thousand paces (of 5 feet each) as measured by every other step—as in the total distance of the left foot hitting the ground 1,000 times, which equals approximately 5,000 ft. In 1592, English Parliament wanted to standardize the measurement of the mile and made the decision that it should be equal to eight furlongs. Furlongs, which are still used as a unit of measurement in horse racing, are 660 feet long. 660 times eight equals, you guessed it, 5,280 ft.</p>
<p>This continued until a major change took place around 200 years ago. As the Age of Discovery came to an end and industry grew primarily in Western Europe, it became necessary to unify units of length on a global scale. In the 17th century, discussions were held in Europe regarding the unification of units. After a century of discussions, France proposed the unit of the meter (meaning "to measure" in Greek) in 1791. The reference at this time was the distance of the meridian from the north pole to the equator. One meter was set as 1/10,000,000 of this distance. Today, one meter is defined as "the distance that light travels in a vacuum in 1/299,792,458 of a second," as defined in 1983.</p>
<p>For navigation on water (marine), air, and space the nautical mile unit of length is used. Historically, a nautical mile was defined as the meridian arc length corresponding to one minute of a degree of latitude.  Nautical mile is based on Earth’s circumference being 360 degrees. These degrees can then be divided into 60 minutes. One of these minutes (or minutes of arc as they are called in navigation) along a great circle on Earth represents one nautical mile. Today the international nautical mile is defined as exactly 1,852 meters (6,076 ft; 1.151 mi).</p>
<p>In terms of statute or land miles, a nautical mile represents 1.15 miles. This is because one degree of latitude is approximately 69 statute miles in length. 1/60th of that measure would be 1.15 statute miles. </p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection  xml:id="" ><title>Length Units</title>

<p>In the US standard system, the inch (in) 1” (double apostrophe) is the primary unit, with the foot (ft) 1’ (single apostrophe) and mile (mi) used for larger distances.</p>
<p>In the metric system, the base unit for length is the meter (m). Its subdivisions include the centimeter (cm), millimeter (mm). The kilometer (km), equivalent to 1,000 m is used for longer distances.</p>
<p>For navigation on water (marine), air, and space, the <term>Nautical Mile</term> (NM) unit of length is used.</p>

<table>
              <title> Length units for US Standard and Metric systems</title>
              <tabular>
                <row header='yes'>
                  <cell>U.S. Standard</cell>
                  <cell>Metric</cell>
                  <cell>Conversions</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>12 inches = 1 foot</cell>
                  <cell>1 centimeter (cm) = 10 millimeters</cell>
                  <cell> 1 inch = 2.54 cm</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>3 feet = 1 yard</cell>
                  <cell>1 meter = 100 centimeters</cell>
                  <cell>1 ft = 0.3048 m</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>1,760 yards = 1 mile</cell>
                  <cell>1 kilometer = 100,000 centimeters</cell>
                  <cell>1 yd = 0.9144 m</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>5,280 feet = 1 mile</cell>
                  <cell> 1 kilometer = 1,000 meters</cell>
                  <cell> 1 mile = 1.6093 km</cell>
                </row>
              </tabular>
            </table>


<table>
              <title> Length units for US Standard and Metric systems</title>
              <tabular>
                <row>
                  <cell> 1 Nautical Mile = 6,076 ft</cell>
                  <cell>1 Standard Mile = 5,280 ft</cell>
                  <cell>1 Kilometer = 3,280.84 ft</cell>
                </row>
              </tabular>
            </table>

<figure xml:id="length_comparison">
<!-- Source:  roger gill/>
  -->
<caption>Visual comparison of Kilometer, Statute Mile and Nautical mile</caption>
<image width="60%" source="images/length_comparison.png"/>
</figure>

<p>Fathom: A nautical measurement equal to 6 feet or 1.8288 meters. It is commonly used for measuring depth in water. Finger tip to finger tip </p>
<p><image width="40%" source="images/fathom.png"/></p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection  xml:id="" ><title>Length Measuring Instruments</title>
<p><term>Rulers and Yardsticks</term>  are straight, flat measuring tools commonly used for shorter lengths. A ruler measure 1 ft. or 12 inches whereas a yardstick measure 3 ft. or 1 yd.</p>
<p></p>
<image width="50%" source="images/ruler.png"/>
<image  width="50%" source="images/yardstick.png"/>
<p></p>
<p>A <term>Tape Measure</term> is a flexible tape marked with inches and feet for measuring longer distances. It is often used in construction and carpentry. </p>
<p> </p>
<image width="50%"  source="images/tapemeasure.png"/>

<p>Calipers or callipers are used to measure he dimensions of an object, generally by placing two movable points of the instrument across the object or span to be measured..</p>
<p></p>
<image  width="50%" source="images/calipers.png"/>

<p>A <term>micrometer</term>, sometimes known as a <term>micrometer screw gauge</term>, is a device incorporating a calibrated screw widely used for accurate measurement of components. Outside, inside, and depth micrometers are all used. The outside micrometer has a unit conversion chart between fractional and decimal inch measurements etched onto the frame</p>
<p></p>
<image  width="50%" source="images/micrometer.png"/>
<p>A <term>surveyor's tape</term> is a long, flexible tape marked in meters used in land surveying.</p>

<p>A <term>sextant</term> is a navigation instrument used to measure the angle between celestial objects and the horizon. It helps determine a ship's position at sea. </p>
<p></p>
<image width="50%"  source="images/sextant.png"/>

<p><term>Microwave instruments</term> use microwaves to take survey measurements. They have a range up to 100 km and are comprised of two identical units, a master unit, and a remote unit.</p>
<p><term>Infrared wave instruments </term>use amplitude modulated infrared waves and prism reflectors. They have a range up to 3 km and accuracy of +/- 10mm.</p>
<p><term>Light wave instruments</term> rely on the propagation of modulated light waves. Their accuracy varies from 0.5mm to 5mm/km, and they have a daytime range of 3km and night range of 2.5km.</p>
<p><term>Laser measuring tools</term> send a beam to the target, which reflects off the surface and is sent back to the device. Lasers are focused beams of light that stay at a particular frequency. And because they travel from one place to another at a fairly constant rate, they can be used to measure distance with a great deal of accuracy. A laser measuring device also has a longer range than many other measuring tools, which gives it an advantage over other devices that become less precise the farther out you measure. Lasers are less likely to disperse than white light, so they can travel at a greater distance without losing their intensity. They keep most of their intensity once they reflect off a target, which is important if you want to get accurate distance measurements.</p>
<image  width="50%" source="images/laser.png"/>
<p><term>Sonar</term> is an object-finding system that uses sound waves to determine the distance, speed of and direction to objects within its range. ..</p>
<p></p>
<image  width="50%" source="images/sonar.png"/>

<p>These instruments allow engineers, sailors, and others to accurately measure lengths and distances according to their respective systems of measurement. It's important to note that many professionals now use digital instruments, such as laser distance measurers, which can provide precise measurements in multiple units.</p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection  xml:id="" ><title>Unit Conversions</title>

<p>Frequently, engineers need to find length equivalents between different systems of measurement. For example, in the construction of a ship there may be different contractors, some of whom use US standard measurement and others who use metric. Since the agreed upon system is metric, conversions are required to standardize all measurements.</p>
<p><term>Conversion of units</term> is the process to convert between different units of measurement for the same quantity, typically through multiplicative <term>conversion factors</term> which change the measured quantity value without changing its effects. Unit conversion is often easier within the metric or the SI than in others, due to the regular 10-base in all units and the prefixes that increase or decrease by 3 powers of 10 at a time.</p>
<p>The <term>unit-factor method</term> or the <term>unity bracket method</term> is a widely used technique for unit conversions using the rules of algebra. </p>
<p>The<term> factor-label method</term> is the sequential application of conversion factors expressed as fractions and arranged so that any dimensional unit appearing in both the numerator and denominator of any of the fractions can be cancelled out until only the desired set of dimensional units is obtained. For example, 10 miles per hour (mi/hr or mph) can be converted to meters per second (m/s) by using a sequence of conversion factors as shown below:</p></subsubsection>

<subsubsection  xml:id="" ><title>Example</title>

<p>Using unit-factor method we can express a distance in meters from feet as:</p>
<p>To Find distance in meters = (distance in ft) <m>\times</m>  (12 in/1 ft) <m>\times</m> (2.54 cm/1 in) <m>\times </m>(1 m/100 cm)</p>
<p>The Conversion factor is .3048 m/ft</p>
<p>distance in meters = (distance in ft) x 0.3048 m/ft</p>
<p>1 foot = 12”/1 ft <m>\times</m> 2.54 cm/1” = 30.48 cm/ft</p>
<p>1 foot = 1 M/100 cm <m>\times</m> 30.48 cm = 0.3048 Meters </p>
<p>Conversion Factor = .3048</p>

<p>1 meter =1ft/12 in <m>\times</m> 1 in/2.54 cm <m>\times</m> 100 cm/1 m=100 /30.48</p>
<p>1 meter = 100/30 =3.28 ft</p>
<p>Conversion Factor</p>
<p>1 foot = 0.3048 m</p>
<p>1 inch = 2.54 cm</p>
<p>Nautical Miles</p>
<p>1 Statute Mile= 1 Statute Mile/5280 ft x 6076 ft/1 NM = 1.15 Mile/NM</p>
<p>Conversion Factor = 1.15 mile/NM</p>

<p>1 km =1.852 NM</p></subsubsection>

<subsubsection  xml:id="" ><title>Example Problem</title>

<p>The last example explains how to convert meters to inches. We start with the same units as in the first example, but finish with different units. There will be two separate conversions. First, we convert from meters to feet. Then we convert from feet to inches. Remember, there are </p>
<p>.</p>
<p>Convert </p>
<p>Feet to Meters</p>
<p>Meters to Feet</p>
<p>Miles to KM</p>
<p>KM to Miles</p>

<p>7 meters to inches. 7 meters × 3.28084 feet</p>


<p> </p></subsubsection>
</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Temperature</title>
<introduction>
<!-- TODO Replace all illustrations in this section with non copyright images -->
<p><term>Temperature</term> is a measure of the average kinetic energy of the particles in a substance. It quantifies how hot or cold an object or environment is relative to a standard or reference point.</p>
<p>The most commonly used temperature scale in the US today is the <term>Fahrenheit scale</term>, abbreviated F. In this scale, water freezes at 32 degrees and boils at 212 degrees. (This only holds strictly when atmospheric pressure equals the average sea level pressure. At high altitudes, water boils at a lower temperature, as anyone who cooks in the mountains knows.)</p>
<p>Another common scale is the <term>Celsius</term> (also called Centigrade) scale. In this scale, water freezes at 0 degrees and boils at 100 degrees.</p>
<p>There are also temperature scales in which zero is the lowest possible temperature, called <term>absolute zero</term>. (People have gotten close to absolute zero, but have never reached it. According to theory, we never will.) Absolute zero is at -273.15 Celsius, or -459.67 Fahrenheit.</p>
<p>The <term>Kelvin</term> temperature scale uses the same size degree as Celsius, but has its zero set to absolute zero.</p>
<p>The <term>Rankine</term> temperature scale uses the same size degree as Fahrenheit, but has its zero set to absolute zero</p>
<p>The Celsius and Kelvin scales are part of the International System of Units (SI), providing a standardized and widely adopted system for expressing temperatures. Celsius is the more common scale for everyday use, while Kelvin is often used in scientific and thermodynamic calculations.</p>
<figure>
<image source="images/temperature-image1.jpg" width="40%"/>
<caption>Temperature Scales</caption>
</figure>
To convert between Fahrenheit and Celsius use these formulas:
<table>
<title>Temperature Conversion Formulas</title>
<tabular>
<row>
<cell>
<url href="https://www.thoughtco.com/convert-celsius-to-fahrenheit-609228">Celsius to Fahrenheit</url>
</cell>
<cell><degree/> F = 9/5 ( <degree/> C) + 32</cell>
</row>
<row >
<cell>
<url href="https://www.thoughtco.com/convert-kelvin-to-fahrenheit-609234">Kelvin to Fahrenheit</url>
</cell>
<cell><degree/> F = 9/5 (K - 273) + 32</cell>
</row>
<row >
<cell>
<url href="https://www.thoughtco.com/fahrenheit-to-celsius-formula-609230">Fahrenheit to Celsius</url>
</cell>
<cell><degree/> C = 5/9 (<degree/> F - 32)</cell>
</row>
<row >
<cell>
<url href="https://www.thoughtco.com/celsius-to-kelvin-conversion-example-609547">Celsius toKelvin</url>
</cell>
<cell>K = <degree/> C + 273</cell>
</row>
<row >
<cell>
<url href="https://www.thoughtco.com/convert-kelvin-to-celsius-609233">Kelvin to Celsius</url>
</cell>
<cell><degree/> C = K - 273</cell>
</row>
<row >
<cell>
<url href="https://www.thoughtco.com/convert-fahrenheit-to-kelvin-609231">Fahrenheit to Kelvin</url>
</cell>
<cell>K = 5/9 (<degree/> F - 32) + 273</cell>
</row>
</tabular>
</table>

<p>These formulas allow you to convert temperatures between different scales. It's important to use the appropriate formula based on the units provided or required for a specific calculation or conversion.</p></introduction>

<subsubsection  xml:id="" ><title>Instruments Used to Measure Temperature</title>

<p>Various instruments are used to measure temperature in different applications. The choice of temperature measurement instrument depends on factors such as the required accuracy, temperature range, and the specific application or industry. Different instruments are suitable for different temperature ranges and environments.</p>
<p>Here are some common instruments used to measure temperature:</p>
<paragraphs><title>Liquid in Glass Thermometer</title>

<p>Liquid in glass thermometers are the most common instruments for measuring temperature.  This type of thermometer uses a temperature sensitive liquid, such as mercury or alcohol, sealed in a glass tube. The liquid expands or contracts with temperature changes, and the temperature is read from a scale on the thermometer. </p>
<figure>
<image source="images/temperature-image2.png"  width="40%"/>
<caption>Liquid in Glass Thermometer</caption>
</figure>
</paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Bimetallic temperature sensors</title>

<p>Bimetallic temperature sensors use the differential expansion of two metals to detect temperature changes. These are often used in thermostats and mechanical temperature gauges.</p>
<figure>
<image source="images/temperature-image3.png"  width="30%"/>
<caption>Bimetallic Thermometer Temperature Sensor</caption>
</figure>
</paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Thermocouple</title>

<p>Thermocouple are made from two different metal wires joined at one end. When exposed to temperature variations, it generates a small electrical voltage proportional to the temperature difference.</p>
<figure>
<image source="images/temperature-image4.png"  width="60%"/>
<caption>Thermocouple Temperature Sensor</caption>
</figure>
</paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Resistance Temperature Detector</title>

<p>Resistance Temperature Detectors (RTD) determine temperature by measuring the resistance of an electrical wire, which increases as the temperature rises and decreases when the temperature falls. The change in resistance of the wire indicates the temperature change.</p>
<figure>
<image source="images/temperature-image5.jpg"  width="40%"/>
<caption> Resistance Temperature Detector RTD </caption>
</figure>
</paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Thermistor</title>

<p>Thermistors are a type of temperature-sensitive resistor whose electrical resistance changes significantly with temperature. They are commonly used in electronic devices and temperature control systems.</p>
<figure>
<image source="images/temperature-image6.gif"  width="40%"/>
<caption>Thermistor</caption>
</figure>
</paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Infrared (IR) Thermometer</title>

<p>An Infrared (IR) thermometer measures temperature without direct contact with the object. It detects the infrared radiation emitted by the object, converting it into a temperature reading. IR thermometers are particularly useful for non-contact measurements or in hazardous environments.</p>
<figure>
<image source="images/temperature-image7.jpg"  width="40%"/>
<caption>Infrared Thermometer</caption>
</figure>
</paragraphs>
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
</section>
</chapter>
</book>
</pretext>