<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- intermediate copy. Process with scriv2ptx.xslt -->
<pretext>
<book xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Introduction to Marine Engineering</title>
<chapter xml:id="introElectricty"> 
<title>Electricity</title>
<p><term>Voltage</term>, or <em>electric potential difference</em>, is a fundamental concept in electricity.  Voltage  is measured in units of volts (V), and symbolized as <m>V</m>.  Voltage can be seen as the <q>push</q> or<q>force</q> that propels electric charges within a circuit. When voltage is applied to a circuit, it creates an electric field that influences the movement of charged particles, resulting in the establishment of an electric current. In simpler terms, voltage serves as the driving force behind the flow of electric charges in an electrical system.</p>
<p>Voltage can be produced through several methods, including <em>chemical reactions</em> (such as in batteries) and the <em>photovoltaic effect</em> (as in solar cells). However, the most important method of is <term>electromagnetic induction</term>.  Electromagnetic induction is the process where a changing magnetic field induces (creates) an electric voltage in a nearby conductor.   This phenomenon is the basis for generating electricity in devices like generators and transformers.  Electrical generators will be described in more detail in <xref provisional="generators"/></p>
<p><term>Current</term> refers to the flow of electric charge in an electrical circuit. It is the rate at which electric charges, typically electrons, move through a <term>conductor</term>. Current is measured in amperes (A) and is represented by the symbol <m>I</m>. It can be thought of as the quantity of charge passing through a point in a circuit per unit of time. The flow of current occurs when there is a potential difference (voltage) applied across a conductor, providing the driving force for the movement of electric charges.</p>
<p><term>Resistance</term> is a property of a material or component in an electrical circuit that opposes the flow of electric current. It is measured in ohms (Ω) and is denoted by the symbol <m>R</m>. Resistance determines the extent to which a material or device hinders the flow of electrical charge. When a voltage is applied across a conductor, the resistance restricts the flow of current, resulting in a decrease in the magnitude of the current. Materials with high resistance impede the flow of electricity more than materials with low resistance. The resistance of a component depends on factors such as its length, cross-sectional area, and the material it is made of.</p>
<p><term>Ohm’s law</term> describes the relationship between current, voltage, and resistance. According to Ohm's Law, the current flowing through a circuit is directly proportional to the voltage across it and inversely proportional to the resistance of the circuit. Mathematically, this relationship is expressed as <me>I = V/R</me>  where: <ul marker="">
<li><m>I</m> is the the current in amperes</li>
<li><m>V</m> is the voltage in volts, and </li>
<li><m>R</m> is the resistance in ohms (Ω). </li>
</ul></p>
<p>In other words, an increase in voltage leads to a corresponding increase in current if the resistance remains constant, while an increase in resistance results in a decrease in current for a given voltage.</p>
<p>An <term>electrical circuit</term> is a complete loop or path that allows for the regulated flow of electric current to power devices and carry out different tasks. It consists of different elements like voltage sources, switches, and electrical loads that are interconnected through wires. <term>Electrical loads</term> refer to devices that consume electrical energy and convert it into another form like mechanical work, light, or heat.   Motors, light bulbs and heating elements are some common examples of electrical loads.  </p>
<p><term>Series Circuit</term>: In a series circuit, the components are connected in a single path such that the same current flows through each component. The components are connected end-to-end, creating a sequential circuit. In a series circuit, the total resistance is the sum of the individual resistances, and the total voltage across the circuit is divided among the components. If one component fails or is disconnected, the entire circuit is broken, and the flow of current stops.</p>

<p><term>Parallel Circui</term>t: In a parallel circuit, the components are connected in multiple paths, allowing the current to divide and flow through different branches simultaneously. Each component in a parallel circuit has the same voltage across it. The total current in the circuit is divided among the branches based on the resistance of each branch. If one component fails or is disconnected in a parallel circuit, the current can still flow through the remaining branches.</p>

<p>In summary, a series circuit has components connected in a single path with the same current flowing through each component, while a parallel circuit has components connected in multiple paths, allowing current to divide among the branches.</p></chapter>
</book>
</pretext>