<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- intermediate copy. Process with scriv2ptx.xslt -->
<pretext>
<book xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Introduction to Marine Engineering</title>
<frontmatter xml:id="frontmatter">
      <titlepage>
        <author>
          <personname/>
          <department>Engineering Department</department>
          <institution>Massachusetts Maritime Academy</institution> 
       </author> 
       <date>
          <today/>
        </date> 
     </titlepage>
 </frontmatter>
<chapter xml:id="safety"> 
<title>Safety</title>
<objectives>
<ul><li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/34.html#RFPEW-A1.3" visual="RFPEW-A1.3"/> Safe working practices as related to engine-room operations</li>
<li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/31.html#OICEW-C1.5" visual="OICEW-C1.5"/> Safety measures to be taken to ensure a safe working environment</li>
<li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/35.html#ABE-C3.1" visual="ABE-C3.1"/> Mechanical safety</li>
<li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/35.html#ABE-C3.1" visual="ABE-C3.1"/> Electrical safety</li>
<li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/35.html#ABE-C3.1" visual="ABE-C3.1"/> Chemical and biohazard safety</li>
</ul>
</objectives>
<introduction>
<p>Ships are dangerous places to live and work for many reasons, some general, and some specific to the marine environment.  These include dynamic and unpredictable marine conditions, extended working hours with small crews, hazardous cargos, isolated work settings, and the potential for fire, explosion, collision, and sinking.</p>
<p>Everyone aboard needs to be aware of the potential hazards, actively engage in safety measures, and be prepared to respond to emergencies.  Safety is not solely the responsibility of designated officers or management but is a collective responsibility shared by all onboard. </p>
<p>In this chapter we discuss some of the hazards you may encounter aboard ship, approaches to managing and reducing risk, and some things you can do personally do to protect yourself, your shipmates, the vessel, and the environment.</p>

</introduction>

<section xml:id=""><title>Hazards in the workplace</title>
<introduction>
<p>In any workplace, including aboard a ship, exposure to safety hazards is inevitable due to the nature of the work environment. These hazards can have serious repercussions such as injuries, operational disruptions, equipment damage, financial loss, environmental harm, and even loss of life. </p>
<p>Identifying, addressing, and avoiding hazards is crucial to maintaining a safe working environment, protecting yourself and others. In this section we describe some common workplace hazards which you should be aware of.</p></introduction>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Slips, Trips and Falls</title>
<p>According to the US Bureau of Labor Statistics, slips, trips, and falls cause nearly 700 fatalities per year and many more injurious accidents in the workplace,</p>
<p>Common trip and fall hazards include obstructions on walkways, such as cables, tools, or equipment left in pathways. Uneven surfaces, loose gratings, and obstructions, can also contribute to tripping incidents. Additionally, poor lighting, cluttered work areas, improper storage of materials, and inadequate lighting can increase the risk of trips and falls.  </p>
<p>Spilled liquids, oils, or water can make surfaces extremely slippery. Wet surfaces due to cleaning or maintenance activities, and the presence of loose debris are additional factors that can contribute to slip incidents.</p>
<p>Falls can be particularly dangerous when you are working at above the ground, such as on a ladder, scaffolding or staging.</p>
<p>Aboard ship, additional hazards exist due to the dynamic and often wet environment. Obstructions such as hatch combings, pad-eyes and container hold-downs can cause individuals to trip. Slip hazards arise from seawater or rainwater on deck surfaces, spilled liquids in galley areas, or lubricants used for machinery maintenance.  In rough seas, the motion of the ship can cause unsecured objects to fall, or cause you to lose your balance and fall. You must be particularly careful when working at heights or over the side. Always follow the old adage, “one hand for the ship and one hand for yourself.</p></subsection>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Mechanical Hazards</title>
<p>Mechanical hazards are a physical hazards associated with machines and other movable objects that may cause harm to a person.</p>
<p>Injuries caused by mechanical hazards include friction or abrasion, lacerations, cutting, severing, pinching, crushing, or entanglement of body parts. Additionally, non-mechanical hazards such as chips, splashes, and sparks can injure you or others in the area.</p>
<figure xml:id="machine-safety">
<caption>Rotating Shaft Hazard Sign</caption>
<image width="50%" source="pics/safety/machine-safety.jpeg">
<!-- Source: https://www.compliancesigns.com -->
</image>
</figure>

<p>Mechanical hazards can be managed by adopting safe work procedures and the application of appropriate safeguards. As such, you should always wear appropriate PPE, follow the machine’s operating instructions, and ensure that all machine safety features and guards are in place. Be aware that some machines may start automatically at any time, so take appropriate precautions including de-energizing and locking out machinery before working on it.</p>
</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Electrical Hazards</title>
<p>Electricity is a powerful and essential source of energy, but it can cause severe injuries, fires, and even fatalities if not handled properly.  Understanding the hazards posed by electricity is crucial for practicing electrical safety.</p>

<figure xml:id="reddy_kilowatt">
<caption> Danger High Voltage </caption>
<image width="40%" source="pics/safety/reddy_kilowatt.jpg">
<!-- Source:  Public Domain  -->
</image>
</figure>
<p>Here are some of the main hazards associated with electricity:</p>
<paragraphs><title>Electrical Shock</title>

<p>The most immediate and dangerous hazard of electricity is electrical shock. When a person comes into contact with an electrical voltage, current can pass through their body, causing electrical shock. </p>
<p>Roughly speaking, the greater the current, the more severe the shock.  High voltage presents more danger than lower voltages, but even normal household voltage (120 V AC) can cause severe shock or even death.</p></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Electrical Burns</title>

<p>Electrical burns occur when electric current passes through the body, generating heat. These burns can be internal or external, depending on the path the electricity takes. Electrical burns can cause extensive tissue damage and may require specialized medical treatment. The severity of electrical burns depends on the voltage, current, duration of contact, and the body's resistance.</p>
</paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Electrocution</title>

<p>In the most severe cases, electric shocks can lead to electrocution, resulting in death. High-voltage shocks can cause cardiac arrest, severe internal injuries, and other life-threatening conditions. Contact with overhead power lines, unauthorized access to electrical panels or equipment, and improper handling of live wires are some situations that can lead to fatal accidents.</p></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Electrical Fires</title>

<p>Electrical malfunctions can generate heat and sparks, leading to electrical fires. Faulty wiring, overloaded circuits, damaged electrical cords, and short circuits are common causes of electrical fires. These fires can quickly spread and pose a significant risk to property and life. The combination of electricity and flammable materials increases the likelihood of a fire and makes it more challenging to extinguish.</p>
</paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Arc Flash and Arc Blast</title>

<p><term>Arc flash</term> refers to the release of intense heat, light, and energy that occurs during an electrical fault or short circuit. It is characterized by a sudden and violent discharge of electrical energy through the air. The arc flash generates extremely high temperatures, often exceeding 35,000 degrees Fahrenheit (19,400 degrees Celsius). The intense heat emitted during an arc flash can cause severe burns to anyone in its vicinity. Additionally, the arc flash produces a bright flash of light, which can lead to temporary or permanent vision impairment.</p>
<p><term>Arc blast</term>, on the other hand, refers to the high-pressure shockwave produced by the rapid expansion of air during an arc flash. The rapid expansion of these vapors creates a blast wave that can cause significant physical damage. Arc blasts can result in powerful pressure waves, similar to those generated by an explosion, which can cause injuries, such as concussions, fractures, hearing loss, and even fatalities. The arc blast can propel debris, molten metal, and hot gases, further exacerbating the risk to individuals in the vicinity.</p></paragraphs>

<assemblage xml:id=''> <title>Effects of Electrical Current on the Human Body</title>

<p>Electrical shock occurs when current passes through the body.  The severity of the shock depends on the current’s magnitude, the duration, the contact area, and the path taken by the current through the body. </p>
<p>The shock current received obeys <xref provisional="ohms-law">Ohm’s law</xref>, so high voltages are always more dangerous.  But your body resistance is equally important.  Body resistance with dry skin may be above 100,000 ohms, However, if the skin is wet or broken, the body's resistance decreases to a few thousand ohms.</p>

<tabular halign="left" width="100%">
              <col width="20%"/> 
             <col width="80%"/>    
<row header="yes" bottom="minor" >
      <cell>Current</cell>
      <cell>Reaction 1 Second contact</cell>
    </row>
<row><cell> &lt; 1 mA </cell><cell><p>Generally not perceptible.</p> </cell></row>
<row><cell>1 mA </cell><cell><p>Threshold of feeling, tingling sensation.</p>  </cell></row>
<row><cell>3 mA </cell><cell><p>Painful shock. Average individual can let go.</p>  </cell></row>
<row><cell>5 mA </cell><cell><p>Accepted as maximum harmless current. Strong involuntary reactions  may cause indirect accidents.</p>   </cell></row>
<row><cell>6<ndash/>25 mA </cell><cell><p>Beginning of sustained muscular contraction. ("Can't let go" current.)</p>  </cell></row>
<row><cell>9<ndash/>30 mA </cell><cell><p>Lung paralysis, Respiratory arrest ‐ usually temporary, but death is possible.</p>  </cell></row>
<row><cell>50 mA </cell><cell><p>Possible ventricular fibrillation. (heart dysfunction, usually fatal.)</p>  </cell></row>
<row><cell>100<ndash/>300 mA </cell><cell><p>Certain ventricular fibrillation, fatal.</p>  </cell></row>
<row><cell>1<ndash/>4 Amps </cell><cell><p>Heart paralysis, severe burns. Muscular contraction and nerve damage occur;
death is likely.</p>  </cell></row>
<row><cell>5 Amps </cell><cell><p>Flesh burns, defibrillation, temporary respiratory paralysis. </p> </cell></row>
</tabular>
</assemblage></subsection>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Chemical Hazards</title>
<p>Chemicals can pose significant risks to human health and safety.  By identifying and understanding the potential hazards, following proper storage and handling procedures, and adhering to safety protocols, you can significantly reduce the risks associated with hazardous chemicals and create a safer environment for everyone.</p>

<figure xml:id="hazardous-material-placards">
<caption> Hazardous Material Placards  </caption>
<image width="90%" source="pics/safety/hazardous-material-placards.jpg">
<!-- Source:  https://airseacontainers.com/blog/how-to-read-and-understand-hazmat-placards/  -->
</image>
</figure>


<paragraphs><title>Chemical Exposure</title>

<p>You may be exposed to hazardous chemicals through inhalation, skin contact, or ingestion. Prolonged exposure or exposure to high concentrations can lead to adverse health effects such as respiratory issues, skin irritation, chemical burns, organ damage, or even long-term illnesses. </p>
<p>You should be aware of the hazardous chemicals present in your workplace, handle them safely and take precautions to minimize exposure, such as using proper ventilation systems, wearing personal protective equipment (PPE), and following established protocols.  </p>
<p>You can learn about the potential risks associated with a chemical, as well as instructions on how to handle and respond to accidents or exposures, in the <term>Material Safety Data Sheet</term> (MSDS), which is required to be available in your workplace. MSDSs are typically created by the manufacturer or supplier of the chemical and are designed to ensure the safe use, storage, and disposal of hazardous substances.</p>
</paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Chemical Storage</title>

<p>Chemicals that are improperly stored or incompatible substances stored in close proximity can react with one another, causing fires, explosions, or the release of toxic gases. Inadequate storage practices may also result in spills, leaks, or contamination, endangering both employees and the environment. </p>
<p>It is essential to follow proper storage procedures, including segregating incompatible chemicals, labeling containers correctly, ensuring proper ventilation and temperature control, and implementing appropriate containment measures such as spill kits and secondary containment systems.  The MSDS will contain instructions regarding proper storage.</p>
<p>In particular, aboard ship chemical containers must always be secured so that they don’t break free and cause accidents during heavy weather.   </p></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Handling and Transporation</title>

<p> Improper handling of hazardous chemicals, such as careless pouring, transferring chemicals without suitable protective measures, or failure to follow established protocols, can result in spills, splashes, or exposure.  </p></paragraphs>
</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Fire </title>

<p>Fire aboard ship is an ever-present threat that can swiftly escalate into a catastrophic disaster. With limited means of escape, a ship becomes a confined space where flames can spread rapidly, fueled by combustible materials and confined by its structure. </p>
<p>The close quarters, complex layout, and intricate ventilation systems aboard ship create formidable challenges for the ship’s small firefighting team. In addition to the immediate threat to human lives, a shipboard fire poses a significant risk to the environment, as toxic smoke, potential oil spills, and the release of hazardous substances can wreak havoc on marine ecosystems. </p>

<figure xml:id="Hyundai_Fortune">
<caption><em>Hyundai Fortune</em> on fire 21 March 2006</caption>
<image width="75%" source="pics/safety/Burning_container_ship_Hyundai_Fortune_yemin-ship-76682.jpg">
<!-- Source:  Royal Netherlands Navy, CC0, via Wikimedia Commons https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Burning_container_ship_Hyundai_Fortune_yemin-ship-76682.jpg  -->
</image>
</figure>
<p>Effective fire prevention measures, comprehensive emergency response plans, rigorous training, and state-of-the-art firefighting equipment are crucial in mitigating this threat and ensuring the safety of everyone on board.</p>
<p>Fire prevention measures play a vital role in minimizing the risk of fire and maintaining a safe environment aboard ship. These measures encompass a range of proactive strategies aimed at preventing fires from starting or spreading. One fundamental aspect is implementing rigorous safety protocols and adhering to international standards, such as the International Maritime Organization's (IMO) regulations for fire safety.</p>
<p>Some key fire prevention measures include:
<ul>
<li><p> <em>Regular Inspections and Maintenance.</em> Conducting routine inspections of electrical systems, machinery, and fire suppression equipment is crucial. Identifying and addressing potential hazards, faulty wiring, or malfunctioning equipment can prevent fire incidents.</p></li>

<li><p> <em>Training and Education.</em> Crew members should receive comprehensive training on fire safety, including proper handling of flammable substances, effective use of firefighting equipment, and emergency response procedures. Increasing awareness and knowledge among the crew can significantly reduce the likelihood of fire-related accidents.</p></li>

<li><p> <em>Fire Detection Systems.</em> Installing advanced fire detection systems, such as smoke detectors, heat sensors, and flame detectors, helps in early detection of fires. These systems can trigger alarms, alerting the crew and initiating immediate response actions.</p></li>

<li><p> <em>Fire Suppression Systems.</em> Equipping ships with reliable fire suppression systems, such as fixed CO2 or water mist systems, can effectively control and extinguish fires. These systems are designed to release the appropriate extinguishing agent in the affected area, limiting the fire's spread.</p></li>

<li><p> <em>Proper Storage and Handling</em>. Storing flammable materials in designated areas and following strict protocols for their handling reduces the risk of accidental ignition. Implementing proper waste management procedures and ensuring the availability of suitable fire-resistant containers also contribute to fire prevention efforts.</p></li>

<li><p> <em>Structural Fire Protection.</em> Regulations require fire-resistant materials and insulation in the ship's construction helps to contain fires and slow down their progression. Fire-resistant doors, bulkheads, and insulation compartmentalize the vessel, preventing the rapid spread of flames.</p></li>

<li><p> <em>Emergency Preparedness.</em> Developing and regularly reviewing comprehensive emergency response plans specific to fire incidents is crucial. This includes establishing evacuation procedures, assigning roles and responsibilities to crew members, and conducting fire drills to ensure everyone knows how to respond swiftly and effectively in an emergency.</p></li>

</ul></p>
<p>By implementing robust fire prevention measures, ships can significantly reduce the risk of fire, enhance the crew's safety, and protect the marine environment from potential devastation.</p>
</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Fatigue</title>
<objectives>
<ul><li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/614.html#PSSR-X6.1" visual="PSSR-X6.1"/> Importance of obtaining the necessary rest</li>
<li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/614.html#PSSR-X6.2" visual="PSSR-X6.2"/> Effects of sleep, schedules, and the circadian rhythm on fatigue</li>
<li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/614.html#PSSR-X6.3" visual="PSSR-X6.3"/> Effects of physical stressors on seafarers</li>
<li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/614.html#PSSR-X6.4" visual="PSSR-X6.4"/> Effects of environmental stressors in and outside the ship and their impact on seafarers</li>
<li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/614.html#PSSR-X6.5" visual="PSSR-X6.5"/> Effects of schedule changes on seafarer fatigue</li>
</ul>
</objectives>
<p>Fatigue, which refers to a state of extreme tiredness and lack of energy, can pose several risks.   The primary cause of fatigue is insufficient or poor-quality sleep.  To avoid fatigue, it's important to prioritize adequate rest and sleep, and maintain a healthy lifestyle.</p>
<p>Other factor which can contribute to fatigue include: medical conditions such as chronic fatigue syndrome, anemia, and thyroid disorders; depression and anxiety, and unhealthy lifestyle habits, including inadequate physical activity, poor nutrition, excessive caffeine or alcohol intake, and smoking. Certain medications have fatigue as a side effect. </p>
<p>The negative consequences of fatigue include:</p>
<p>Fatigue can significantly impair cognitive abilities, including attention, concentration, memory, and decision-making. This can lead to reduced performance and increased errors, particularly in tasks that require sustained focus or critical thinking, such as driving, operating machinery, or performing complex work.</p>
<p>Fatigue can slow down reaction times and impair alertness, making it more challenging to respond quickly and appropriately to stimuli or unexpected events. This can increase the risk of accidents, both in occupational settings and during activities like driving or operating heavy equipment.</p>
<p>Fatigue-related impairment can lead to an increased risk of accidents and injuries across various domains, including workplaces, roadways, and other high-risk environments. Fatigue-related accidents have been linked to major incidents in industries such as transportation, healthcare, and manufacturing.</p>
<p>Fatigue can impair an individual's ability to assess risks accurately and make sound judgments. This can result in poor decision-making, potentially leading to safety hazards or negative consequences in various aspects of life, including personal relationships and professional responsibilities.</p>
<p>The IMO has developed guidelines for rest requirements to address the issue of fatigue among seafarers. These guidelines are outlined in the International Convention on Standards of Training, Certification, and Watchkeeping for Seafarers (STCW Convention). </p>
<p>The STCW Convention sets out minimum hours of rest for seafarers. The standard requires that seafarers receive a minimum of 10 hours of rest in any 24-hour period and a minimum of 77 hours of rest in any 7-day period. The hours of rest may be divided into no more than two periods, with one period being at least 6 hours in length.</p>
<p>In situations where the safety of the ship, crew, or passengers is compromised, and in cases of emergencies or drills, the rest period may be temporarily shortened or interrupted. However, the seafarers should be provided with compensatory rest as soon as possible.</p>
</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Confined Spaces</title>
<objectives>
<ul><li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/35.html#ABE-C3.1" visual="ABE-C3.1"/> Working in enclosed spaces</li>
<li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/614.html#PSSR-X3.3" visual="PSSR-X3.3"/> Precautions to be taken prior to entering enclosed spaces</li>
</ul>
</objectives>
<p>A confined space is defined by OSHA as a space that has limited or restricted means of entry, is not designed for continuous occupancy, and is large enough and configured so that a person can enter the space and maneuver well enough to perform tasks.  </p>
<p>Confined spaces pose several hazards that can endanger workers who enter  them due to their limited entry and exit points, restricted airflow, and potential for hazardous atmospheres. </p>
<p>On ships, some examples of confined spaces include:  Cargo and fuel tanks, cofferdams, pressure vessels, sewage tanks, and void spaces. </p>

<figure xml:id="confined-space-sign">
<caption> Confined Space Hazards  </caption>
<image width="50%" source="pics/safety/confined-space-sign.png">
<!-- Source:  smartsign.com  -->
</image>
</figure>
<p>Here are some hazards associated with confined spaces:</p>
<paragraphs><title>Lack of oxygen</title>

<p>Confined spaces often have limited ventilation, which can lead to a decrease in oxygen levels. This oxygen-deficient atmosphere can cause dizziness, loss of consciousness, or even asphyxiation.</p></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Toxic gases and vapors</title>

<p>Confined spaces may contain hazardous gases or vapors, such as carbon monoxide, hydrogen sulfide, or volatile chemicals. These substances can accumulate in the confined space and pose a serious health risk to individuals who inhale them, leading to poisoning or respiratory problems.</p></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Fire and explosion risks</title>

<p>Confined spaces may contain flammable substances, inadequate electrical systems, or potential ignition sources. This combination can result in the rapid escalation of fire or explosion hazards, especially in spaces with limited airflow and potential fuel accumulation.</p>
</paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Engulfment or entrapment</title>

<p>Confined spaces often have small openings or tight access points. If an individual becomes trapped or engulfed by materials, such as loose soil, water, or flowing grain, it can lead to serious injury, suffocation, or drowning.</p></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Physical hazards</title>

<p>Confined spaces may have uneven surfaces, protruding objects, or low ceilings, increasing the risk of slips, trips, falls, and head injuries. Limited visibility and restricted movement within the space can further contribute to accidents and make rescue difficult.</p></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Extreme temperatures</title>

<p>Some confined spaces can experience extreme temperatures due to insulation issues, lack of ventilation, or the presence of heat-generating equipment. Excessive heat or cold can cause thermal discomfort, heat exhaustion, hypothermia, or heat stroke.  </p>
<p>Emergency repairs to boilers must sometimes be made before the boiler has had a chance to cool down.</p>
</paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Biological hazards</title>

<p>In certain confined spaces, such as sewage tanks or areas with stagnant water, there may be an increased risk of exposure to bacteria, viruses, or mold, which can lead to respiratory issues, allergies, or infectious diseases.</p>
</paragraphs>

<p>For safe entry into a confined space, everyone involved should be properly trained on confined space entry and rescue techniques and strictly comply with all regulations and guidelines governing confined space entry. </p>
<p>Begin by conducting a thorough risk assessment to identify potential hazards and establish necessary control measures. Inspect the equipment used for entry to guarantee its reliability. </p>
<p>Ensure proper ventilation is in place, to maintain fresh air and remove hazardous substances. Test the atmosphere using gas detection equipment before entering to verify safe conditions. Wear the appropriate personal protective equipment (PPE), including respiratory protection and fall protection gear. </p>
<p>Maintain proper lighting to ensure visibility within the confined space. Establish effective communication systems between individuals inside and outside the space. Designate a standby person outside the space, equipped with rescue training, to provide immediate assistance if required. </p>
</subsection>
</section>

<section xml:id=""><title>Hazard Mitigation</title>
<objectives>
<ul><li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/31.html#OICEW-C2.1" visual="OICEW-C2.1"/> Safe isolation of shipboard machinery and equipment before personnel are permitted to work</li>
<li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/31.html#OICEW-C2.1" visual="OICEW-C2.1"/> Safety measures to be taken for repair and maintenance</li>
<li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/35.html#ABE-C3.1" visual="ABE-C3.1"/> Permit to work systems</li>
</ul>
</objectives>
<introduction>
<p>TBD</p></introduction>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Safety Management</title>
<introduction>
<p>Safety management is a systematic approach taken by regulatory bodies and companies to identify, assess, control, and mitigate risks in order to ensure the safety of personnel, assets, and the environment. It involves the development and implementation of policies, procedures, and practices aimed at preventing accidents, injuries, and damage. </p>
<p>Key components of safety management include risk assessment, safety planning, establishment of policies and procedures, training and education, reporting and investigation of incidents, audits and inspections, and continuous improvement efforts. The goal of safety management is to protect lives, prevent harm, and promote a culture of safety within organizations across various industries.</p></introduction>

<subsubsection  xml:id="" ><title>ISM Code</title>

<p>The International Safety Management Code (ISM Code) is a set of guidelines and regulations developed by the International Maritime Organization (IMO) to ensure the safe operation of ships and the prevention of marine pollution. It was adopted in 1993 and became mandatory for all vessels engaged in international voyages in 1998.</p>
<p>The primary objective of the ISM Code is to establish a safety management system (SMS) on board ships and ashore, providing a framework for managing safety and minimizing risks in the maritime industry. The code applies to all types and sizes of vessels, including passenger ships, cargo ships, tankers, and offshore drilling units.</p>
<p>Under the ISM Code, both the ship and the company have specific obligations to ensure the effective implementation of safety management systems and adherence to safety standards. The obligations of the ship and the company are as follows:</p>
<paragraphs><title>Ship Obligations</title>

<p> <ul>
<li>Implement the Safety Management System (SMS): The ship is responsible for implementing and following the SMS as defined by the company. This includes adhering to the documented procedures and instructions outlined in the SMS.</li>
<li>Report Hazards and Non-conformities: The ship is obligated to report any hazards, accidents, or non-conformities that may affect the safety of the ship, its personnel, or the environment. This includes reporting incidents, near-misses, and deficiencies in the SMS.</li>
<li>Participate in Training and Drills: All personnel on board the ship must undergo appropriate training to ensure they have the necessary skills and knowledge to perform their duties safely. They are also required to actively participate in safety drills and exercises.</li>
<li>Comply with Safety Procedures: The ship must comply with all safety procedures and guidelines outlined in the SMS. This includes following safe working practices, adhering to emergency response plans, and utilizing safety equipment as required.</li>
<li>Maintain Records: The ship is responsible for maintaining accurate records of safety-related activities, including incidents, inspections, audits, drills, and maintenance activities. These records provide evidence of compliance with the ISM Code.</li>
</ul></p></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Company Obligations</title>

<p><ul> 
<li>Develop and Implement the SMS: The company is responsible for developing and implementing a documented Safety Management System (SMS) for each ship under its management. The SMS should encompass policies, procedures, and instructions that promote safe operations and environmental protection.</li>
<li>Appoint a Designated Person Ashore (DPA): The company must appoint a Designated Person Ashore (DPA) who serves as a liaison between the company and the ship. The DPA ensures that the SMS is effectively implemented, maintained, and continuously improved.</li>
<li>Provide Adequate Resources: The company must provide the necessary resources, including personnel, equipment, training, and support, to enable the ship to comply with the ISM Code and operate safely.</li>
<li>Conduct Audits and Reviews: The company is responsible for conducting internal audits and reviews of the SMS to assess its effectiveness and identify areas for improvement. These audits ensure that the SMS is being followed and that any non-conformities are addressed.</li>
<li>Maintain Documentation: The company must maintain comprehensive documentation of the SMS, including policies, procedures, instructions, and records. This documentation serves as evidence of compliance and provides a reference for shipboard personnel.</li>
</ul></p>
</paragraphs>

<p>By fulfilling these obligations, everyone works together to promote a culture of safety, prevent accidents, protect the environment, and continuously improve the safety standards in the maritime industry.</p></subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Job Hazard Analysis</title>
<p>A <term>job hazard analysis</term> (JHA), also known as a job safety analysis (JSA), is a systematic process used to identify and analyze potential hazards or risks associated with specific job tasks or activities. Its primary purpose is to reduce the risk of accidents by identifying potential hazards and developing appropriate controls to mitigate them.</p>
<p>The process typically involves breaking down a job into its individual steps  and examining each step to identify potential hazards. Hazards can include physical hazards (e.g., machinery, equipment, or environmental conditions), chemical hazards (e.g., exposure to hazardous substances), biological hazards (e.g., exposure to infectious agents), ergonomic hazards (e.g., repetitive motion or lifting heavy objects), or any other factors that could pose a risk to worker safety and health.</p>
<p>The key steps in conducting a job hazard analysis typically include: 
<ol>
<li>Select the job or task to be analyzed.</li>
<li> Break down the job into steps.</li>
<li> Identify potential hazards for each step.</li>
<li><p> Determine the risk level for each identified hazard.  Risk level multiplies severity and the likelihood of each identified hazard.</p></li>

<li> Develop hazard controls to eliminate or minimize the hazards. This might include engineering controls (e.g., machine guarding), administrative controls (e.g., training or procedures), or personal protective equipment (PPE)</li>
<li> Communicate the findings to workers and stakeholders to ensure awareness and buy-in.</li>
<li>Regularly review and update the job hazard analysis.</li>
</ol></p>
<p>This results of the JHA can be shared with the crew during a <term>toolbox talk </term>in order to raise awareness about known hazards, reinforce safe work practices, and promote a culture of safety. These talks are usually conducted before the start of the work day.</p>
<p>Systematically analyzing and communicating job hazards and implementing appropriate controls helps to create a safer workplace. </p>
<figure xml:id="safety-jha">
<caption>Sample Job Hazard Analysis Form</caption>
<image source="pics/safety/jha.png"/></figure>
</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Lock out-Tag out</title>
<objectives>
<ul><li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/35.html#ABE-C3.1" visual="ABE-C3.1"/> Lockout/tag-out</li></ul>
</objectives>
<p>tbd</p></subsection>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Permit to work </title>
<p>A <term>permit to work</term> is a document used to control hazardous activities conducted onboard a ship. It is a written authorization that specifies the work to be performed, identifies the potential hazards involved, and outlines the necessary precautions and safety measures.</p>
<p>Permits to work are required for dangerous jobs such as hot work  (welding or burning), confined space entry, working at heights, electrical work, handling hazardous substances, hoisting operations, etc. </p>
<p>The permit to work system is designed to prevent accidents, injuries, and damage to the ship and its equipment by ensuring that work activities are conducted in a controlled manner. It helps to manage high-risk tasks and ensure that proper procedures are followed. </p>

<figure xml:id="hot-work-tag">
<caption>Hot Work Tag</caption>
<image width="75%" source="pics/safety/hot-work-tag.png">
</image>
<!-- Source:  https://www.idescosafety.com/  -->
</figure>
</subsection>
</section>

<section xml:id=""><title>Personal Safety</title>
<objectives>
<ul><li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/614.html#PSSR-X3.1" visual="PSSR-X3.1"/> Importance of adhering to safe working practices at all times</li>
<li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/614.html#PSSR-X3.2" visual="PSSR-X3.2"/> Safety and protective devices available to protect against potential hazards aboard ship</li>
<li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/31.html#OICEW-D8.4" visual="OICEW-D8.4"/> Knowledge of personal safety</li>
<li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/35.html#ABE-C3.1" visual="ABE-C3.1"/> Lifting techniques and methods of preventing back injury</li>
<li><url href="https://weh.maritime.edu/stcw/2023/tables/34.html#RFPEW-A3.2" visual="RFPEW-A3.2"/> Know escape routes from machinery spaces</li>
</ul>
</objectives>
<p>Safety in the workplace is everyone’s responsibility, but no one is more responsible for your own personal safety than you! Here are some key safety practices to follow to ensure your own safety.</p>
<p><ul>
<li> <title>Maintain Situational Awareness</title>

<p>Always be attentive and aware of your surroundings and what is going on around you. Pay attention to potential hazards, changing conditions, and any applicable safety instructions or procedures.  Make sure you are familiar with the escape routes from the space you are in, and the location of the nearest fire extinguisher.</p></li>
<li> <title>Follow Safe Working Procedures</title>

<p>Familiarize yourself with the safe working procedures for your assigned tasks and follow them meticulously. These procedures are designed to minimize risks and ensure your safety. Seek guidance if you are unsure about any aspect of your tasks.</p></li>
<li> <title>Use PPE </title>

<p>Wear the appropriate personal protective equipment for your tasks and the specific hazards you may encounter. This includes hard hats, safety glasses, gloves, and safety footwear. Make sure your PPE is in good condition and fits properly.</p></li>
<li> <title>Maintain Cleanliness and Organization</title>

<p>Keep your work area clean, organized, and free of clutter. Properly stow tools and equipment after use to prevent trip hazards. Promptly clean up any spills or debris to maintain a safe working environment.</p></li>
<li> <title>Practice Safe Lifting Techniques</title>

<p>To lift heavy objects safely, follow these guidelines:</p>
<p>Assess the object's weight and plan your lift accordingly. Warm up your muscles with light exercises. Stand close to the object with feet shoulder-width apart, keeping your back straight and bending at the knees. Get a firm grip on the object and lift using the strength of your legs, not your back. Avoid twisting and keep the object close to your body. </p>
<p>Don’t hesitate to ask for help if you need it. Prioritize safety and listen to your body to prevent injuries.</p></li>
<li> <title>Maintain Personal Fitness and Well-being</title>

<p>Ensure you are physically and mentally fit for the tasks assigned to you. Get enough rest, eat well, and stay hydrated. Fatigue and exhaustion can compromise your alertness and increase the risk of accidents.  Don’t abuse alcohol or drugs, and certainly don’t attempt to perform your duties when you’re impaired.</p></li>
<li> <title>Follow Emergency Procedures</title>

<p>Familiarize yourself with the ship's emergency procedures, including evacuation routes, muster stations, and the proper use of life-saving equipment. Be prepared to respond calmly and promptly in case of an emergency.</p></li>
<li> <title>Practice Good Communication</title>

<p>Safety is a team effort. Maintain open and effective communication with your fellow crew members.  Share safety-related information, ask questions, and seek clarification when needed. Don’t hesitate to speak up if you notice safety hazards, near misses, or unsafe practices.  Effective communication is essential for preventing, addressing and resolving safety issues promptly.</p>
</li>
<li> <title>Learn Continuously</title>

<p>Stay proactive in expanding your safety knowledge and skills. Participate in safety training programs, attend safety briefings, and stay updated on safety regulations and best practices. Take safety drills seriously.  The more informed you are, the better equipped you will be to protect yourself contribute to a safe working environment.</p></li>
</ul></p>
<p>By following these safety practices, you will not only protect yourself but also contribute to the overall safety of the crew and the smooth operation of the ship. Remember, safety should always be your top priority.</p></section>
</chapter>

<chapter xml:id="ppe"> 
<title>Personal Protective Equipment</title>
<introduction>
<p>Personal protective equipment (PPE) includes all clothing and other work accessories designed to create a barrier against workplace hazards. It provides an important link in the chain of workplace safety, but PPE alone is not a substitute for safe engineering design, proper training, good work practices, safety awareness, or hazard reduction. All these elements together are required to minimize the danger of workplace hazards and maximize the safety and health of workers.   </p>
<p>Using personal protective equipment requires hazard awareness and training on the part of the user. You must be trained to know when personal protective equipment is necessary, what type is necessary, how it is to be worn, and what its limitations are, as well as know its proper care, maintenance, useful life, and disposal. In addition, you must be aware that the equipment does not eliminate the hazard. If the equipment fails, you can be injured. To reduce the possibility of failure, equipment must be properly fitted, and maintained in a clean and serviceable condition. </p>
<p>To protect yourself, you must be wearing the proper personal protective when it is needed and recognize its limitations. The equipment must not be altered or removed even though you may find it uncomfortable. In some cases however, the equipment may be uncomfortable because it does not fit properly. </p>
<p>In this chapter we will discuss some of the personal protective equipment normally found and used aboard ship. </p>
</introduction>

<section xml:id=""><title>Head Protection</title>

<p>Introduction</p>
<paragraphs><title>Types of Head Protection</title>

<p>There are several types of hard hats available, each designed for specific purposes and levels of protection. Here are some common types of hard hats:</p>
<p>   <term>Class A.</term> Class A hard hats and caps are intended for general service and they provide protection against impact hazards and a limited protection against electrical shock. They are used in industries such as construction, manufacturing, mining, and shipbuilding. This is the most suitable hard hat for shipboard use. </p>


<p>   <term>Class B.</term> Class B hard hats are utility service hats which are designed to protect the wearer’s head from impact and penetration by falling or flying objects and from high-voltage shock and burns. They are used extensively by electrical workers. </p>

<figure xml:id="hardhats_jpg">
   <caption>Hard Hat</caption>
   <image source="pics/ppe/hardhats.jpg"/>
</figure>

<p>   <term>Class C.</term> The safety hat or cap in Class C is designed specifically for lightweight comfort and impact protection and is sometimes known as a bump cap. Class C helmets are used on occasions where there is a possibility of bumping the head against a fixed object and no danger from falling objects or electrical shock. Bump caps can be worn for protection against scalp lacerations from contact with sharp objects. However, they are not substitutes for safety caps/hats because they do not afford protection from high impact forces or penetration by falling objects. </p>

</paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Fit</title>


<p>Correct adjustment and fit of the your hard hat is required for maximum safety. The internal cradle of the headband and sweatband forms a suspension system which keeps the helmet away from the head and cushions against impact. The headband must be adjusted to the right size in order to provide sufficient clearance between the shell and the headband. </p>


<p>Before using a hard hat you should inspect it for signs of damage or abuse of the helmet or any of its parts. A damaged helmet reduces the margin of safety the hat was designed to supply, and should be replaced immediately. </p>

</paragraphs>

</section>

<section xml:id=""><title>Eye Protection</title>

<p>Introduction</p>
<paragraphs><title>Types of Eye Protection</title>


<p>The three main types of eye protection for general maintenance are safety glasses, goggles, and face shields. In addition, when welding, specialized equipment must be used to protect your eyes. Each method of eye protection has its own advantages and disadvantages. </p>


<p>   <term>Safety Glasses.</term> Safety glasses are lightweight glasses that have shatter resistant lenses made of materials like polycarbonate or propionate plastic and often have side shields attached to the side pieces. Safety glasses are designed to stop flying objects such as chips, fragments, sand, and dirt from injuring your eyes. They also can provide laser light filtration to prevent reflections from the laser entering the eye and causing retinal burns. Safety glasses can be purchased with prescription lenses including bifocals if necessary. </p>


<p>The main advantage of safety glasses is that they are lightweight and relatively comfortable to wear for long periods of time. The provide little to no protection from liquids or vapors, and some flying particles may get around the side shields. </p>

<figure xml:id="goggles_jpg">
   <caption>Types of Eye Protection</caption>
   <image source="pics/ppe/goggles.jpg"/>
</figure>

<p>   <term>Goggles.</term> Goggles provide more complete protection of the eye than safety glasses, since they protect against both frontal and side impact. They come in two different types, vented and non-vented. Vented goggles are used to protect your eyes from splashes and flying objects, while Non-vented Goggles additionally protect your eyes from hazardous vapors, mists, and fumes. </p>


<p>   <term>Face Shields.</term> Face shields are designed to augment other types of eye protection and are not meant to be a stand alone form of eye protection. Face shields are used to protect your entire face with goggles on under the shield to catch any liquids that might make it past the shield. </p>

</paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Eye Protection for Welding</title>


<p>Always wear a welding helmet when arc welding. Your eyes, face, and neck need protection against the burning rays of the arc, and from the splatter of molten metal and slag. To protect your eyesight, make sure the welding helmet has a coloured lens with at least a No. 10 shade when welding with 200 amperes or less. And never strike a welding arc before your helmet is in place. Never look at an arc from any distance with your naked eyes while someone else is welding. </p>


<p>Never chip slag when your eyes (or those of others nearby) are not protected by goggles, an eye shield, or the clear lens of a welding helmet. If fragments of hot slag were to hit the eye, medical attention would be required for their removal, and blindness could result. The risk of permanent eye injury is so great that you should never chip slag from a weld without protecting your eyes. </p>

</paragraphs>

</section>

<section xml:id=""><title>Hearing Protection</title>

<p>Introduction</p>
<paragraphs><title>Types of Hearing Protectors</title>

<p>There are various types of hearing protection available to safeguard against excessive noise levels. Here are some common types:</p>
<figure xml:id="Hearing_Protection_png">
   <caption>Types of Hearing Protection</caption>
   <image source="pics/ppe/Hearing_Protection.png" width="50%"/>
</figure>
<p>   <term>Disposable foam plugs.</term> Foam plugs are inexpensive devices made of a formable material designed to expand to fit to the shape of each person’s ear canal. To use, roll the expandable plugs into a thin, crease-free cylinder, and insert it into the ear canal. Apply a slight pressure to the plug until the foam completely expands. These plugs can be reused a couple of times, but never reuse them if they have become dirty. Some people may find that the standard expandable plug is too large for their ear canal, and may find that the smaller plug model fits better. </p>
<p>   <term>Reusable, pre-molded plugs.</term> Pre-molded plugs are made from silicone, plastic or rubber and are manufactured as either <q>one-size-fits-most</q> or are available in several sizes. Be sure to choose the proper size for your ear canals. In some cases, different size plugs may be required for each ear. The advantage of pre-molded plugs are that they are inexpensive, reusable, washable, convenient to carry, and come in a variety of sizes. Nearly everyone can find a plug that will be comfortable and effective. Another advantage is that in a dirty environment like the engine room, you don’t need to handle or roll the tips. You insert this type of plug by reaching over your head with one hand to pull up on your ear. Then use your other hand to insert the plug with a gentle rocking motion until you have sealed the ear canal. </p>
<p>   <term>Hearing Bands.</term> Hearing Bands, also called canal caps or semi-insert devices often resemble earplugs on a flexible plastic or metal band. The earplug tips of a canal cap may be a formable or pre-molded material. Some have headbands that can be worn over the head, behind the neck or under the chin. The main advantage of canal caps is their convenience They are easy to put on and take off . When it’s quiet, employees can leave the band hanging around their necks, but they can quickly insert the plug tips when hazardous noise starts again. These devices are ideal for intermittent use, but they provide less protection then either plugs or muffs. Some people find the pressure from the bands uncomfortable. </p>
<assemblage xml:id="what_is_a_decibel">
   <title>What is a Decibel?</title>
<p>The Decibel (dB) is a logarithmic unit used to describe a ratio. The ratio may be power, or voltage or intensity or several other things. To get a taste for logarithmic units, first let’s look at some numbers: Suppose we have two loudspeakers, the first playing a sound with power <m>P_1</m>, and another playing a louder version of the same sound with power <m>P_2</m>, but everything else (how far away, frequency) is kept the same. The difference in decibels between the two is given by <me>10 \log (P_2/P_1) \text{ dB}</me> where the log is to base 10. </p>
<p>If the second produces twice as much power than the first, the difference in dB is <me> 10 \log (P_2/P_1) = 10 \log 2 = 3 \text{ dB}</me>. If the second had 10 times the power of the first, the difference in dB would be <me>10 \log (P_2/P_1) = 10 \log 10 = 10 \text{ dB}</me>B. If the second had a million times the power of the first, the difference in dB would be <me> 10 \log (P_2/P_1) = 10 \log 1,000,000 = 60 \text{ dB} </me>. This example shows one feature of decibel scales that is useful in discussing sound: they can describe very big ratios in power with numbers of modest size. </p>
<p>Sound is usually measured with microphones and they respond (approximately) proportionally to the sound pressure, <m>p</m>. The power in a sound wave is approximately equal to the square of the pressure. Since the log of the square of <m>x</m> is just <m> 2 \log x </m>, this introduces a factor of 2 when we convert to decibels for pressures. Therefore the difference in sound pressure level between two sounds with <m>p_1</m> and <m>p_2</m> is defined as: <me> 20 \log (p_2/ p_1) \text{ dB}</me> where the log is to base 10. </p>
<p>This formula involves a ratio of pressures, so to measure the sound level for a single sound, a reference level must be chosen. For sound intensity, the reference level (for air) is usually chosen as 20 micropascals, or 0.02 mPa. This is very low: it is 2 ten billionths of an atmosphere. Nevertheless, this is about the limit of sensitivity of the human ear, in its most sensitive range of frequency. Usually this sensitivity is only found in rather young people or in people who have not been exposed to loud music or other loud noises. Personal music systems with in-ear speakers are capable of very high sound levels in the ear, and are responsible for much of the hearing loss in young adults in developed countries. So if you read of a sound intensity level of 86 dB, it means that <m>20 \log (p_2/p_1) = 86 </m> dB where <m>p_1</m> is the sound pressure of the reference level, and <m>p_2</m> that of the sound in question. Divide both sides by 20: <m>\log (p_2/p_1) = 4.3 </m> dB. 4 is the log of 10 thousand, 0.3 is the log of 2, so this sound has a sound pressure 20 thousand times greater than that of the reference level. 86 dB is a loud but not dangerous level of sound, if it is not maintained for very long. </p>
<p>What does 0 dB mean? This level occurs when the measured intensity is equal to the reference level. i.e., it is the sound level corresponding to 0.02 mPa. In this case we have sound level <me> = 20 \log (p / p_{ref}) = 20 \log 1 = 0 \text{ dB}</me>. So 0 dB does not mean no sound, it means a sound level where the sound pressure is equal to that of the reference level. This is a small pressure, but not zero. It is also possible to have negative sound levels: - 20 dB would mean a sound with pressure 10 times smaller than the reference pressure, i.e. 2 micropascals. </p>
</assemblage>
</paragraphs>

</section>

<section xml:id=""><title>Respiratory Protection</title>

<p>Introduction</p>
<paragraphs><title>Types of Respirators</title>


<p>OSHA divides respirators into two categories: </p>

<figure xml:id="respirators1_jpg">
   <caption>Air-purifying respirator</caption>
   <image source="pics/ppe/respirators1.jpg" width="50%"/>
</figure>
<p>   <term>Air-purifying Respirators.</term> These units have filters, cartridges, or canisters that remove contaminants from the air by passing the air through the air-purifying element before it reaches the user. Air purifying respirators are further divided into: <ul>
<li><em>Particulate Respirators</em>, which capture particles such as dusts, paint fumes, and mists, but do not protect against gases and vapors. The filters in particulate respirators generally work better as particles accumulate on the filter. If the filter becomes so clogged that it is difficult to breathe, it should be replaced. </li>
<li>            <em>Gas and Vapor Respirators</em>, which use a chemical cartridge or canister to remove dangerous gases or vapors, but which do not protect against airborne particles. These units only protect against specific gases or vapors, and only provide protection as long as the filter’s absorbing capacity remains. </li>
<li>            <em>Combination Respirators</em>, which can be used in atmospheres that contain both hazardous gases and particles. </li>
</ul></p>

<figure xml:id="respirators2_jpg">
   <caption>Atmosphere-supplying respirators</caption>
   <image source="pics/ppe/respirators2.jpg" width="50%"/>
</figure>

<p>   <term>Atmosphere-supplying Respirators.</term> These units supply clean air directly to the user from a source other than the air surrounding the user. The types of air-supplying respirators are:    <ul>
<li>            <em>Air Supplied Respirators</em>, which have a hose which connects to a source of clean air under pressure. These units have no time limit on the air supply, but the hose limits the range and mobility of the user and is susceptible to damage. </li>
<li>            <em>Self-Contained Breathing Apparatus</em>, which have a wearable clean-air supply pack. These units have better mobility than the air-supplied respirator, but the clean air time is limited to the capacity of the tank. </li>
<li>            <em>Combination Respirators</em>, which are similar to the air-supplied respirators, but also have a small, self-contained air supply which can be used for escape if the primary supply fails. </li>
   </ul></p>
</paragraphs>

</section>

<section xml:id=""><title>Arm and Hand Protection</title>

<p>Introduction</p>
<paragraphs><title>Types of Gloves</title>

<p>There is a broad selection of safety gloves available to protect your hands from workplace hazards. For example:  <ul>
<li>Disposable Gloves - protects against mild irritants and bodily fluids </li>
<li>Rubber Lineman’s Gloves and sleeves - protects against shock when working on live wires </li>
<li>Metal Mesh Gloves - protects against accidental cuts when using knives </li>
<li>Chemical Resistant Gloves - proper selection of material can resists chemical attack </li>
<li>Cleanroom Gloves - maintains cleanliness of electronic parts </li>
<li>Cotton Work Gloves - improves grip and protects from heat and cold </li>
<li>General Purpose Leather Gloves - protects against cuts and moderate temperatures </li>
<li>Temperature Resistant Gloves - protects from high temperatures </li>
<li>Welder’s Gloves - protects from high temperatures and sparks </li>
</ul></p></paragraphs>

</section>

<section xml:id=""><title>Foot Protection</title>

<p>Introduction</p>

<p><term>Safety Shoes and Boots.</term> Safety shoes and boots are available in many styles depending on the job requirements. Boots provide more protection than shoes from chemicals and molten metals splashes and spark hazards, but they are heavier. Some protective features that are available in both boots and shoes include: <ul>
<li>Oil resistant shoes </li>
<li>Chemical resistant shoes </li>
<li>Heat resistant shoes </li>
<li>Slip and skid resistant shoes </li>
<li>Waterproof and water resistant shoes </li>
</ul></p>
<p><term>Steel-Reinforced Safety Shoes and Boots</term> Similar to safety shoes, these have the toe box and insole reinforced with steel, and the instep reinforced with steel, aluminum, or plastic. These shoes will protect your feet from falling objects and puncture injuries. </p>
<p><term>Composite-Toe Safety Shoes</term> Composite-toe shoes have a protective cap made of non-metallic materials such as carbon fiber, Kevlar, or fiberglass. They offer lightweight protection and are ideal for environments where metal detection is required or in situations where electrical conductivity needs to be minimized.</p>
<p><term>Electrically Insulated Safety Shoes</term> These shoes have non-conductive soles to prevent the wearer’s feet from completing an electrical circuit to ground. They can protect workers against as much as 600 volts in dry conditions. These shoes should be used in conjunction with insulated tools and precautions to reduce or eliminate the potential for providing a path for hazardous electrical energy. Non-conductive footwear must not be used in explosive or hazardous locations; in such locations, electrically conductive shoes are required. </p>
<p><term>Electrically Conductive Safety Shoes</term> These shoes protect against the buildup of static electricity. Essentially, these shoes ground the employees wearing them. Employees working in explosive and hazardous locations such as explosives manufacturing facilities or grain elevators must wear conductive shoes to reduce the risk of static electricity buildup on an employee’s body that could produce a spark and cause an explosion or fire. During training, employees must be instructed not to use foot powder or wear socks made of silk, wool, or nylon with conductive shoes. Foot powder insulates and retards the conductive ability of the shoes. Silk, wool, and nylon produce static electricity. Conductive shoes are not general-purpose shoes and must be removed upon completion of the tasks for which they are required. Employees exposed to electrical hazards must <em>never</em> wear conductive shoes. </p>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter xml:id="marineEngineering"> 
<title>Marine Propulsion</title>
<section xml:id=""><title>Introduction</title>
<paragraphs><title>Introduction overview</title>

<p>tbd</p></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Marine Propulsion</title>

<p>tbd</p></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Modes of propulsion</title>

<p>tbd</p></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Gas Turbines</title>

<p>tbd</p></paragraphs>

<p>tbd</p>
<paragraphs><title>Propellers, Thrusters, Pods, and Jets</title>

<p>tbd</p>
</paragraphs>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter xml:id="thermodynamics"> 
<title>Principles of Thermodynamics</title>
<introduction>
<p> <em>Adapted from Principles of Naval Engineering</em>The process of generating steam is basically simple. You boil water and continue to add heat until the water turns into steam. But how can this steam cause a ship to move through the water? How can steam provide power for steering, ventilation, refrigeration, distillation of seawater, and all the other needs of the vessel? </p>
<p>Steam does not do any of these things directly. But some of the thermal energy contained in the steam can be converted into other forms of energy to move the ship through the water and to provide power for vital shipboard services. </p>
<p>In this chapter we will discuss some basic ideas of energy and some of the important energy transformations that occur in the engineering plant of a steam-driven ship. Study this chapter carefully. The information given here will not help you to light off a boiler, clean firesides, stand a watch, or wipe up oil from the floorplates; however, it will help you to understand the generation of steam, the use of steam in the shipboard engineering plant, and the relationship of the boilers to the rest of the engineering plant. Understanding the information given in this chapter will also give you a sound background for understanding some of the more complicated things that you will have to learn as you advance. </p>
<p>As you study this chapter, watch out for unfamiliar definitions. Many of the words and terms used will be familiar to you, but the definitions we use may be more precise than the ones you have heard before. Be sure that you understand the exact meaning of each word and term used in connection with energy and energy transformations. </p></introduction>

<section xml:id=""><title>Force</title>

<p>What is force? In simple terms, a force is a push or a pull. More precisely, a force is a  vector quantity which tends to produce an acceleration of a body in the direction of its  application. This means that if you want a stationary object to move, you must apply a force  to it to get it going. If you want to keep it moving, you need to continuously apply a force  to it to overcome friction, which is itself a force. Forces can exist without motion too –  when an object is stationary it’s usually because there are many forces acting on it which  cancel each other out, leaving no net force acting on the object. Forces always occur in  pairs. A push on an object is always accompanied by an equal and opposite force acting on the  pusher. </p>
<p>In the English system of units, force is measured in pounds, tons, or long tons. In the SI  system, force is measured in newtons (N) or kilonewtons (kN). For estimation purposes, a  newton is about a quarter of a pound. </p>
<p>One important force which we experience every day is weight. Weight is the force of gravity  - the attraction between an object and the earth. The weight force exerted on an object is  proportional to the mass of the object according to Newton’s second law, which states:  <me>W = mg</me> where <em>W</em> is the weight, <em>m</em> is the mass, and <em>g</em> is the  gravitational constant. </p>
<p>The constant <em>g</em> depends on where you are: on earth the constant is greater than it  is on the moon, so you weigh less on the moon than you do on earth. In outer space, the  constant is zero, making you weightless there. Be careful not to confuse weight with mass. The  mass of an object will not change when it moves to another location, but its weight may. One  reason why people often confuse weight with mass is because in the English system and on the  surface of the earth, the gravitational constant <em>g</em> is equal to 1, and so one pound of  mass has a weight of one pound of force. Move to the moon, and the pound of mass now weighs  about six tenths of a pound. On earth in the SI system, <em>g</em> is approximately equal to  9.81 <m>\textrm{m/s}^2</m>. </p>
</section>

<section xml:id=""><title>Pressure</title>
<introduction>
<p>Pressure is defined as force per unit area. That is, a force acting over an area is a <em>pressure</em>, and when you multiply a pressure by the area that it acts over, you get a force. <me> P = \frac{F}{A} \qquad \text{or} \qquad F = PA </me>Many different units are used to describe pressure. The simplest pressure units are ones that indicate how much force is applied to an area of a certain size. These units include pounds per square inch, pounds per square foot, newtons per square meter, kilopascals, bars or others depending upon the system being used. Aboard ship we most commonly use pounds per square inch (psi). </p>
</introduction>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Head</title>

<p>You will also find another kind of pressure unit, which appears to be a length. These units include inches of water, inches of mercury (Hg), or the height of some other liquid of known density. These units, while measured in length units, still represent a pressure. The length describes the pressure exerted by a column of liquid of the given height, and is known as the <em>head</em>. </p>
<p>For example, a pressure reading of 1 inch of water (1 in. H₂O) means that the exerted pressure is equal to the pressure exerted by a column of water 1 inch high, or that a column of water in a U-tube would be displaced 1 inch by the pressure being measured. Similarly, a reading of 12 inches of mercury (12 in. Hg) means that the measured pressure is sufficient to support a column of mercury 12 inches high. </p>
<p>What is really being expressed, even though it is not mentioned in the pressure unit, is the fact that a certain quantity of material (water, mercury, etc.) of known density will exert a certain definite force upon a specified area. Pressure is still force per unit area even if the pressure unit refers to the height of some liquid. </p>
</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Atmospheric Pressure</title>

<p>Atmospheric pressure is the pressure exerted by the weight of the atmosphere. At sea level the average pressure of the atmosphere is sufficient to support a column of mercury (Hg) 760.0 millimeters or 29.92 inches high. This is equivalent to a pressure of approximately 14.7 psi. This is known as the absolute pressure of the atmosphere, and is indicated by the unit <em>psia</em> (pounds per square inch, absolute) </p>
<p>A barometer is the device used to measure the pressure of the atmosphere, so the absolute pressure of the atmosphere is also known as the barometric pressure. When you hear a weather report, this is the value reported. The barometric pressure changes with weather conditions, but for most purposes aboard ship, this fact can be ignored, and we can assume that the atmospheric pressure is 14.7 psia or 760 mm Hg. at all times. Notice, however, that the figure of 14.7 pounds per square inch absolute (psia.) represents the average atmospheric pressure at sea level, and does not always represent the actual pressure being exerted by the atmosphere at the moment that a gage is being read. </p>
</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Gage Pressure</title>

<p>Since the absolute atmospheric pressure is always present, and acts on everything equally, we normally don’t even notice it. Pressures are usually measured up or down from atmospheric pressure, and an ordinary pressure gage reads zero when it is subjected to atmospheric pressure only. Pressures measured in this way is called the gage pressure. It is important to distinguish between gage pressure and the absolute pressure described in the next section. </p>
</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Absolute Pressure</title>

<p>Pressure measured on a scale increasing from zero at a perfect vacuum is known as absolute pressure. Absolute pressure is always higher than the corresponding gage pressure by the amount of the atmospheric pressure. For shipboard purposes, you can simply add 14.7 psi to the gage reading in psi to get the absolute pressure. For example, a gage pressure of 100 psig would be the same as an absolute pressure of 114.7 psia. </p>
<p>We sometimes say psig to indicate gage pressure and other times we merely say psi. By common convention, gage pressure is always assumed when pressure is given in pounds per square inch, pounds per square foot, or similar units. The <q>g</q> (for gage) is added only when there is some possibility of confusion. Absolute pressure, on the other hand, is always expressed as pounds per square inch absolute (psia), pounds per square foot absolute (psfa), and so forth. It is always necessary to establish clearly just what kind of pressure we are talking about, unless this is very clear from the nature of the discussion. </p>
</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Vacuum</title>

<p>A pressure below atmospheric pressure is called a vacuum. The farther below the atmospheric pressure, the greater the vacuum. Vacuum can not be made greater and greater without limit, however. At some point, the absolute pressure drops as low as possible and a perfect vacuum is achieved. A perfect vacuum is the lowest possible pressure, or the absence of all pressure. When we speak of a <q>high</q> vacuum, we are talking about a low absolute pressure. </p>
<p>When measuring a vacuum, there are three possible methods. When vacuum is measured starting with zero at perfect vacuum and increasing as pressure rises, then the greater the value, the smaller the vacuum. This is known as the absolute pressure scale. We can also measure pressure on a scale starting at zero at atmospheric pressure, and indicating negative values when the pressure is below atmospheric (vacuum) and positive values when the pressure is above atmospheric. This is the behavior of a standard pressure gage. And finally, we can measure vacuum on a scale starting with zero at atmospheric pressure and increasing as the vacuum increases. Most vacuum gages operate this way. On this scale no vacuum would be indicated by 0 psig, and a perfect vacuum would be indicated by approximately 14.7 psi vacuum. </p>
<p>The most common scale used on vacuum gages aboard ship display vacuum in inches of mercury, with the vacuum gage scale marked from 0 to 30 inches of mercury. When this gage reads zero, the pressure in the space is the same as atmospheric pressure or, in other words, there is no vacuum. A vacuum gage reading of 29.92 inches of mercury would indicate a perfect (or nearly perfect) vacuum. In actual practice, it is impossible to obtain a perfect vacuum even under laboratory conditions. </p>
</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Pressure Conversions</title>

<p>In interpreting pressure measurements, a great deal of confusion arises because the zero point on most pressure gages represents atmospheric pressure rather than zero absolute pressure, and both pressure and head scales are used. Thus it is important to specify the kind of pressure being measured under given conditions. To clarify the numerous meanings of the word pressure, the relationship among gage pressure, atmospheric pressure, vacuum, and absolute pressure is illustrated in <xref ref="PressureRelations_png"/>. </p>
<figure xml:id="PressureRelations_png"> <caption>Pressure Relationship</caption> <image source="pics/thermo/PressureRelations.png"/>
</figure>
<p>If you can remember the following facts, it is relatively easy to perform unit conversions between the various pressure scales.</p>
<p>Atmospheric pressure equivalents: <ul>
<li><md>
<mrow> \text{Atmospheric Pressure \amp= 14.7 \text{ psi} </mrow>
<mrow> \amp = 29.92 \textrm{ in Hg} </mrow>
<mrow> \amp = 760 \textrm{ mm Hg} </mrow>
<mrow> \amp = 34 \textrm{ ft H}_2\textrm{O} </mrow>
<mrow> \amp= 101.3 \textrm{ kPa} </mrow>
<mrow> \amp= 1.01 \textrm{ bar}</mrow></md>
</li>
<li>Absolute scales measure up from zero </li>
<li>Gage scales measure up or down from atmospheric pressure </li>
<li>Vacuum scales measure down from atmospheric pressure </li>
</ul></p>
<example xml:id=''><title>psia to vacuum conversion</title>
<statement><p>Convert from 10.4 psia to mm Hg Vacuum </p>
</statement>
<answer>
<p>10.4 psia = 222.3 mm Hg (vacuum)</p></answer>

<solution>
<p><ol>
<li> <p> Set up a ratio to convert psia to mm Hg Absolute 
<md>
<mrow>\frac{10.4 \textrm{ psia}}{14.7 \textrm{ psia}} \amp= \frac{p}{760 \textrm{ mm Hg} }</mrow>
<mrow>\amp = 537.7 \textrm{ mm Hg (absolute)}</mrow></md></p></li>
<li> <p> Subtract from atmospheric pressure to get vacuum
<me>V = 760 - p = 222.3 \textrm{ mm Hg (vacuum)}</me> </p></li>
</ol></p></solution>
</example>
</subsection>
</section>

<section xml:id=""><title>Energy</title>
<introduction>
<p>Can you define energy? Although everyone has a general idea of the meaning of energy, a good definition is hard to find. Most commonly, perhaps, energy is defined as the <q>ability of a system to do work.</q> This is not a very complete definition. Energy can produce other effects which cannot possibly be considered <q>work.</q> For example, heat can flow from one object to another without doing work; yet heat is a form of energy, and the process of heat transfer is a process that produces an effect. </p>
<p>A better definition of energy, therefore, states that <q>energy is the capacity for producing an effect.</q> Energy exists in many forms. For convenience, we usually classify energy according to the size and nature of the bodies or particles with which it is associated. Thus we say that <em>Mechanical energy</em> is the energy associated with large bodies or objects, usually, things that are big enough to see. <em>Thermal energy</em> is energy associated with molecules. <em>Chemical energy</em> is energy that arises from the forces which bind the atoms together in a molecule, Chemical energy is demonstrated whenever combustion or any other chemical reaction takes place. <em>Electro-magnetic</em> energy is energy that is associated with the electron and charged particles. Light, x-rays and radio waves are examples of electro-magnetic energy. <em>Nuclear energy</em> is associated with the particles in the nucleus, and is governed by Einstein’s famous equation <m>E = mc^2</m>nEach of these types of energy (mechanical energy, thermal energy, etc.) must also be classified as being either stored energy, or energy in transition.  <em>Stored energy</em> can be thought of as energy that is actually <q>contained in</q> or <q>stored in</q> a substance or system. There are two kinds of stored energy: potential energy, and kinetic energy. When energy is stored in a substance or system because of the relative <em>positions</em> of two or more objects or particles, we call it potential energy. When energy is stored in a substance or system because of the relative <em>velocities</em> of two or more objects or particles, we call it kinetic energy.  </p>
      <p>
        <ol>
          <li>
            <p> Mechanical Energy – energy associated with relatively large bodies or objects. </p>
            <p>
              <ol>
                <li>
                  <p> Stored forms of mechanical energy </p>
                  <p>
                    <ol>
                      <li>
                        <p> Mechanical potential energy </p>
                      </li>
                      <li>
                        <p> Mechanical kinetic energy </p>
                      </li>
                    </ol>
                  </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <p> Mechanical energy in transition </p>
                  <p>
                    <ol>
                      <li>
                        <p> Work </p>
                      </li>
                    </ol>
                  </p>
                </li>
              </ol>
            </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p> Thermal Energy – energy associated with the very small particles called molecules. </p>
            <p>
              <ol>
                <li>
                  <p> Stored forms of thermal energy </p>
                  <p>
                    <ol>
                      <li>
                        <p> Internal potential energy </p>
                      </li>
                      <li>
                        <p> Internal kinetic energy </p>
                      </li>
                    </ol>
                  </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <p> Thermal energy in transition </p>
                  <p>
                    <ol>
                      <li>
                        <p> Heat </p>
                      </li>
                    </ol>
                  </p>
                </li>
              </ol>
            </p>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </p>
<p>If you do not completely understand this classification, come back to it from time to time as you read the following sections on mechanical energy and thermal energy. The examples and discussion given in the following sections will probably help you to understand this classification. </p>
</introduction>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Mechanical Energy</title>
<introduction>
<p>Let’s consider first the two stored forms of mechanical energy. </p>
<p>Mechanical <em>potential</em> energy exists because of the relative positions of two or more objects. For example, a rock resting on the edge of a cliff in such a position that it will fall freely if pushed has mechanical potential energy. Water at the top of a dam has mechanical potential energy. A sled that is being held at the top of an icy hill has mechanical potential energy. </p>
<p>Mechanical <em>kinetic</em> energy exists because of the relative velocities of two or more objects. If you push that rock, open the gate of the dam, or let go of the sled, something will move. The rock will fall; the water will flow; the sled will slide down the hill. In each case the mechanical potential energy will be changed to mechanical kinetic energy. Another way of saying this is <q>energy of position will be changed to energy of motion.</q></p>
<p>In these examples, you will notice that an external source of energy is used to get things started. Energy from some outside source is required to push the rock, open the gate of the dam, or let go of the sled. All real machines and processes require this kind of <q>boost</q> from an energy source outside the system. For example, there is a tremendous amount of chemical energy stored in fuel oil; but this energy will not raise steam in the boiler until you have expended some energy to start the oil burning. Similarly, the energy in any one system affects other energy systems. However, it is easier to learn the basic principles of energy if we forget about all the energy systems that might be involved in or affected by each energy process. In the examples given in this chapter, therefore, we will consider only one energy process or energy system at a time, disregarding both the energy <q>boosts</q> that may be received from outside systems and the energy transfers that may take place between the system we are considering and other systems. </p>
<p>Notice that both mechanical potential energy and mechanical kinetic energy are stored forms of energy. It is easy to see why we regard mechanical potential energy as being stored, but it is not so easy to see the same thing about mechanical kinetic energy. Part of the trouble comes about because mechanical kinetic energy is often referred to as <q>the energy of motion,</q> thus leading to the false conclusion that <q>energy in transition</q> is somehow involved. This is not the case, however. Work is the only form of mechanical energy that can be properly considered as energy in transition. </p>
<p>If you have trouble with the idea that mechanical kinetic energy is stored, rather than in transition, think of it like this. A bullet that has been fired from a gun has mechanical kinetic energy because it is in motion. The faster the bullet is moving, the more kinetic energy it has. There is no doubt in anybody’s mind that the bullet has the capacity to produce an effect, so we may safely say that it has energy. Although the bullet is in transition, the energy of the bullet is not transferred to any other object or system until the bullet strikes some object which resists its passage. When the bullet strikes against a resisting object, then, and only then, can we say that energy in transition exists, in the form of heat and work. </p>
<p>In this example, we are ignoring the fact that some work is done against the resistance of the air and that some heat results from the passage of the bullet through the air. But this does not change the basic idea that kinetic energy is stored energy rather than energy in transition. The air must merely be regarded as a <q>resisting object</q> which causes some of the stored kinetic energy of the bullet to be converted into energy in transition (heat and work) while the bullet is passing through the air. However, the major part of the stored kinetic energy does not become energy in transition until the bullet strikes an object firmer than air which resists its passage. </p>
<p>In the English system of units, mechanical potential energy is measured in foot-pounds. Consider, for example, the rock at the top of the cliff. If the rock weighs 5 pounds and if the distance from the rock to the earth at the base of the cliff is 100 feet, 500 foot-pounds of mechanical potential energy exist because of the relative positions of the rock and the earth. Another way of expressing this idea is by the formula:  </p>
<p><me>PE = mgh</me></p>
<p>Where: 
<ul marker="">
<li><m>PE</m> = potential energy (in foot-pounds) </li>
<li><m>mg</m> = total weight of the object (in pounds) </li>
<li><m>h</m> = distance between the earth and the object (in feet) </li>
</ul></p>
<p>Mechanical kinetic energy is also measured in foot-pounds. The amount of kinetic energy present at any one time is directly related to the velocity of the moving object and to the weight of the moving object. <me>KE = \frac{1}{2} mv^2</me></p>
<p>Where: <ul marker=""> 
<li><m>KE</m> = Kinetic energy </li>
<li><m>m</m> = Mass of object </li>
<li><m>v</m> = Velocity of object relative to earth </li>
</ul></p>

<p>Mechanical potential energy can be changed into mechanical kinetic energy. If you push that 5-pound rock over the edge of the 100-foot cliff, it begins to fall, and, as it falls, it loses potential energy and gains kinetic energy. At any given moment, the total amount of mechanical energy (potential plus kinetic) stored in the system is the same - that is, 500 foot-pounds. But the proportions of potential energy and kinetic energy are changing all the time as the rock is falling. Just before the rock hits the earth, all the stored mechanical energy is kinetic energy. As the rock hits the earth, the kinetic energy is changed into energy in transition-that is, work and heat. </p>
<p>Mechanical kinetic energy can likewise be changed into mechanical potential energy. For example, suppose you throw a baseball straight up in the air. The ball has kinetic energy while it is motion, but the amount of kinetic energy decreases and the amount of potential energy increases as the ball travels upward. When the ball has reached its uppermost position, just before it starts to fall back to earth, it has only potential energy. Then, as it falls back toward the earth, the potential energy is changed into kinetic energy again. </p>
</introduction>

<subsubsection  xml:id="" ><title>Work</title>

<p>Mechanical energy in transition is called <em>work.</em> When an object is moved through a distance against a resisting force, we say that work has been done. The formula for calculating work is:  <me>W=Fd</me></p>
<p>Where: <ul marker=""> 
<li><m>W</m> = work (in foot-pounds)  </li>
<li><m>F</m> = force (in pounds) </li>
<li><m>d</m> = distance moved in direction of applied force (in feet)  </li>
</ul></p>
<p>As you can see from this formula, you need to know how much force is exerted and the distance through which the force acts before you can find how much work is done. The unit of force is the pound. When work is done against gravity, the force required to move an object is equal to the weight of the object. Why? Because weight is a measure of the force of gravity or, in other words, a measure of the force of attraction between an object and the earth. How much work will you do if you lift that 5-pound rock from the bottom of the 100-foot cliff to the top? You will do 500 foot-pounds of work-the weight of the object (5 pounds) times the distance (100 feet) that you move it against gravity. </p>
<p>We also do work against forces other than the force of gravity. When you push an object across the deck, you are doing work against friction. In this case, the force you work against is not only the weight of the object; but also the force required to overcome friction and slide the object over the surface of the deck. </p>
<p>Notice that mechanical potential energy, mechanical kinetic energy and work are all measured in the same unit, foot-pounds. One foot-pound of work is done when a force of 1 pound acts through a distance of 1 foot. One foot-pound of mechanical potential energy or mechanical kinetic energy is the amount of energy that is required to accomplish 1 foot-pound of work. </p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection  xml:id="" ><title>Power</title>

<p> <em>Power</em> is the rate of doing work. The amount of work done has nothing at all to do with how long it takes to do it. When you lift a weight of 1 pound through a distance of 1 foot, you have done 1 foot-pound of work, regardless of whether you do it in half a second or half an hour. A device which can do a lot of work quickly is powerful. The common unit of measurement for power is the <em>horsepower</em> (hp). By definition, 1 horsepower is equal to 33,000 foot-pounds of work per minute or 550 foot-pounds of work per second. Thus a machine that is capable of doing 550 foot-pounds of work per second is said to be a 1-horsepower machine. (As you can see, your horsepower rating would not be very impressive if you did 1 foot-pound of work in half an hour. Figure it out. It works out to be just a little more than one-millionth of a horsepower.) </p>
</subsubsection>
</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Thermal Energy</title>
<introduction>
<p>All substances are composed of molecules. The energy associated with molecules is called thermal energy. Thermal energy, like mechanical energy, exists in two stored forms and in one transitional form. The two stored forms of thermal energy are called internal potential energy, and internal kinetic energy. Thermal energy in transition is called <em>heat.</em>Although molecules are too small to be seen, they behave in some ways pretty much like the larger objects we considered in the discussion of mechanical energy. Molecules have energy of position (internal potential energy) because of the forces which attract molecules to each other. In this way, they are somewhat like the rock and the earth we considered before. Molecules have energy of motion (internal kinetic energy) because they are constantly in motion. Thus, the two stored forms of thermal energy-internal potential energy and internal kinetic energy-are in some ways similar to mechanical potential energy and mechanical kinetic energy, except that everything is on a smaller scale. </p>
</introduction>

<subsubsection  xml:id="" ><title>Temperature</title>

<p>You are probably already familiar with temperature, and know that we use is it to describe how hot or cold an object is, but what, exactly is it? Temperature is not energy and it’s not heat. It is simply a number related to the average kinetic energy of the molecules of a substance; the greater the average kinetic energy, the greater the temperature. Notice that temperature is not equal to the kinetic energy, just proportional to it, and temperature readings do not tell you anything directly about the potential energy of the substance. </p>
<p>Temperature can be measured in a variety of scales. When the temperature scale is measured up from the point where there is no molecular motion, it is known as an absolute scale, and is directly proportional to the average kinetic energy of the molecules in the substance. The Kelvin and Rankine scales are absolute scales. We normally use the Fahrenheit or Celsius scales, which are offset from the corresponding absolute scale, and so are only indirectly related to the kinetic energy. </p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection  xml:id="" ><title>Internal Energy</title>

<p>Although the term may be unfamiliar to you, you probably know more about <em>internal energy</em> than you realize. Because molecules are constantly in motion, they exert a pressure on the walls of the pipe, boiler, cylinder, or other object in which they are contained. Also, the temperature of any substance arises from, and is directly proportional to, the activity of the molecules. Therefore, every time you read thermometers and pressure gages you are finding out something about the amount of internal energy contained in the substance. High pressures and temperatures indicate that the molecules are moving rapidly and that the substance therefore has a lot of internal energy. </p>
<p>For most purposes, we will not need to distinguish between the two stored forms of thermal energy. Therefore, instead of referring to internal potential energy and internal kinetic energy, from now on we will simply use the term <q>internal energy.</q> By internal energy, then, we will mean the sum total of all internal energy stored in the substance or system because of the motion of the molecules and because of the forces of attraction between molecules. </p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection  xml:id="" ><title>Heat</title>

<p> <em>Heat</em> is a more familiar term than internal energy, but may actually be more difficult to define correctly. The important thing to remember is that heat is <em>thermal energy in transition</em> - that is, it is thermal energy that is moving from one substance or system to another. </p>
<p>An example will help to illustrate the difference between heat and internal energy. Suppose there are two equal lengths of pipe made of identical materials and containing steam at the same pressure and temperature. One pipe is well insulated; the other is not insulated at all. From everyday experience you know that more heat will flow from the uninsulated pipe than from the insulated pipe. When the two pipes are first filled with steam, the steam in one pipe contains exactly as much internal energy as the steam in the other pipe. We know this is true because the two pipes contain equal volumes of steam at the same pressure and at the same temperature. After a few minutes, the steam in the uninsulated pipe will contain much less internal energy than the steam in the insulated pipe, as we can tell by measuring the pressure and the temperature of the steam in each pipe. What has happened? Stored thermal energy - internal energy - has moved from one system to another, first from the steam to the pipe, then from the uninsulated pipe to the air. This movement or flow of thermal energy from one system to another is called heat. </p>
<p>A good deal of confusion exists concerning the use of the word <q>heat.</q> For example, you will hear people say that a hot object <q>contains</q> a lot of heat when they really mean that it contains a lot of internal energy. Or you will hear that heat is <q>added to</q> or <q>removed from</q> a substance. Since heat is the flow of thermal energy, it can no more be added to a substance than the flow of water could be added to a river. (You might add water, and this addition might increase the flow; but you could hardly say that you had added flow.) The only kind of thermal energy that can in any sense be added to or removed from a substance is internal energy. The distinction between heat and internal energy must be clear in your own mind before you can understand the basic principles of a steam plant. Remember, steam contains internal energy but it does not <q>contain heat.</q> Heat exists when the internal energy flows from the steam to something else (another substance or system). </p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection  xml:id="" ><title>Enthalpy</title>

<p>When discussing a system involving work and heat, such as a boiler and turbine, you may hear the term <em>enthalpy.</em> Enthalpy is a thermodynamic quantity defined as the sum of internal energy and the work done by the substance to move its surroundings out of the way as it moves or expands, known as <q>flow work.</q> One consequence of this definition is that when heat flows into a substance at constant pressure, its enthalpy increases by the amount of heat energy added. This is why enthalpy is sometimes described as the <q>heat content</q> of a substance. Remember that heat is energy in transition, and is never stored so no substance ever really <q>contains</q> heat. </p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection  xml:id="" ><title>Units of Measurement</title>

<p>In engineering, temperature is commonly measured in degrees Fahrenheit. In this scale, the boiling point of water at atmospheric pressure is designated 212°, and the freezing point is 32° with 180 equal degrees between. When working in the metric system, the Celsius scale is used. The Celsius scale (sometimes called the centigrade scale) uses zero as the freezing point of water and 100° as its boiling point, with 100 equal divisions or degrees between. </p>
<p>To convert from Celsius to Fahrenheit: multiply by 1.8 and add 32.  <me>°\mathrm{F} = (1.8 \times °\mathrm{C}) + 32°</me>The British thermal unit (BTU) is used to measure heat. Originally, 1 BTU was defined as the quantity of energy required to raise the temperature of 1 pound of water through 1° on the Fahrenheit (F) scale. A similar unit called the calorie (cal) was originally defined as the quantity of heat required to raise the temperature of 1 gram of water through 1° on the Celsius (C) scale. The BTU and calorie are still in use, but the original definitions have been abandoned by international agreement. These units are now defined in terms of the unit of energy called the <q>joule.</q> By definition, 1 BTU is equal to 1054.886 joules, and 1 cal is equal to 4.18605 joules. As may be seen, the BTU is a much larger unit than the calorie; 1 BTU is equal to approximately 252 cal. </p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection  xml:id="" ><title>Heat Transfer</title>

<p>Heat can flow from one substance to another only when a temperature difference exists. Heat flow can occur only from a higher temperature to a lower temperature. When two objects at different temperatures are placed in contact with each other (or near each other), heat flows from the warmer object to the cooler one until both are at the same temperature. Heat transfer occurs at a faster rate when there is a larger temperature difference between the two objects. As the temperature difference approaches zero, the rate of heat transfer approaches zero. </p>
<p>Conduction, radiation, and convection are usually considered to be the three methods by which heat transfer can occur. It is more accurate, however, to consider conduction and radiation as the two basic methods of heat transfer and to consider convection separately as a special process which involves movement within a mass of fluid. </p>

<paragraphs><title>Conduction</title>

<p>Conduction is the method by which heat flows from a hotter to a colder substance when there is physical contact between the two substances. For example, consider a cold metal bar which is held firmly against a piece of red-hot metal. In a short time, the end of the bar which is not touching the hotter metal will have become too hot to hold. We say that heat has been conducted from molecule to molecule, throughout the entire bar. The process of conduction will continue as long as there is a temperature difference between the two ends of the bar. </p>
</paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Radiation</title>

<p>Radiation is a mode of heat transfer that does not require any physical contact between the warmer substance and the cooler substance. For example, a person sitting near a hot stove is warmed by radiant heat even though the air between the person and the stove may remain cold. Similarly, radiant heat from the sun warms the earth without warming the space through which it passes. </p>
</paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Convection</title>

<p>At the molecular or sub-molecular level, heat transfer takes place through both the processes of conduction and radiation. If we use the term <q>heat transfer</q> in a somewhat different way, we may also include convection as a mode of heat transfer. However, it is important to understand the difference between convection and the basic heat transfer processes of conduction and radiation. </p>
<p>If we put a hot brick into a wheelbarrow and wheel it across the street, we have in one sense <q>transferred</q> heat. However, any heat transfer that takes place between the brick and its surroundings while we are wheeling it across the street will be by conduction and by radiation. Therefore, it would really be more accurate to say that we have <q>transported</q> the brick and all its contained thermal energy from one side of the street to the other. </p>
<p>Convection occurs only in fluids – liquids, gases, and vapors – not in solids, such as the brick we have just transported in the wheelbarrow. Convection is the transportation or movement of some portions of a fluid within the total mass of the fluid. As this movement occurs, the moving portions of the fluid transfer their contained thermal energy from one part of the fluid to another. The effect of convection is thus to mix the various portions of the fluid; the part that was at the bottom of the container may move to the top, or the part that was at one side may move to the other side. As this mixing takes place, heat transfer occurs from one part of the fluid to another and between the fluid and its surroundings. But this heat transfer, like any other heat transfer, takes place by conduction and by radiation. In other words, convection transports portions of the fluid; conduction and radiation transfer the thermal energy. </p>
<p>Convection serves a vital purpose in bringing the different parts of the fluid into close contact so that heat transfer can occur. Without convection, there can be little heat transfer from or within fluids. Most fluids are poor conductors of heat when they are not in motion. </p>
<p>What causes this transportation of a mass of fluid? In the case of <em>natural convection</em>, the movement is caused by differences in the density of different parts of the fluid. The differences in density are usually caused by unequal temperatures within the mass of fluid. For example, as the air over a hot radiator is heated, it becomes less dense and therefore begins to rise. Cooler, heavier air is drawn in to replace the heated air, and convection currents are thus setup. Another example of natural convection is the circulation of water in a natural circulation boiler. As the water in the generating tubes is heated, it expands and becomes much lighter (less dense) than the cooler water in the downcomers. Therefore the hotter and lighter water rises, while the cooler and heavier water flows downward. The resulting circulation of water in the boiler is thus clearly an example of convection currents established by differences in temperature (and therefore differences in density) in various parts of the fluid. </p>
<p>In the case of <em>forced convection</em>, some mechanical device such as a pump or a fan produces the movement of the fluid. When the main feed pump moves feedwater toward the boiler, the water is transported by forced convection. The flow of combustion gases through a boiler is partly by natural convection and partly by forced convection. Natural convection occurs because the gases of combustion are hotter and lighter than air, so they tend to rise and go up the stack. Forced convection is also involved in this process, however, because the forced draft blowers supply an air pressure which increases the rate at which the combustion gases travel across the tubes and up the stack. When you stir a cup of hot coffee, you are forcing convection and thus increasing the rate of heat transfer. Natural convection currents would be set up in the coffee if you did not stir it, because differences in density would occur as some portions of the coffee cooled before others. If you want to cool the coffee rapidly, use forced convection (stirring). If you do not want it to cool so rapidly, wait for natural convection to do the job. </p>
<p>In summary, then, we use the term convection to describe the transportation, or loosely, the <q>heat transfer</q> of a mass of fluid and its contained thermal energy. However, the processes by which any substance gains or loses thermal energy are most accurately described in terms of conduction and radiation. </p>
</paragraphs>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection  xml:id="" ><title>Sensible Heat and Latent Heat</title>

<p>The terms <em>sensible heat</em> and <em>latent heat</em> are often used to indicate the effect that the flow of heat has on a substance. The flow of heat from one substance to another is normally reflected in a temperature change in each substance-the hotter substance becomes cooler; the cooler substance becomes hotter. However, the flow of heat is not reflected in a temperature change in a substance that is in the process of changing from one physical state (solid, liquid, or gas) to another. When the flow of heat is reflected in a temperature change, we say that sensible heat has been added to or removed from the substance. When the flow of heat is not reflected in a temperature change but is reflected in the changing physical state of a substance, we say that latent heat has been added or removed. </p>
<p>Does anything bother you in this last paragraph? It should. Here we are, talking about adding and removing heat. And, furthermore, we are talking about sensible heat and latent heat as though we had two different kinds of heat to consider. As noted before, this is common (if inaccurate) engineering language. So keep the following points clear in your mind: (1) heat is the flow of thermal energy; (2) when we talk about adding and removing heat, we mean that we are providing temperature differentials so that thermal energy can flow from one substance to another; and (3) when we talk about sensible heat and latent heat, we are talking about two different kinds of effects that can be produced by heat, but not about two different kinds of heat. </p>
<p>The three basic physical states of all matter are <em>solid,</em> <em>liquid,</em> and <em>gas</em> (or vapor). The physical state of a substance is closely related to the distance between molecules. The molecules are closest together in solids, farther apart in liquids, and farthest apart in gases. When the flow of heat to a substance is not reflected in a temperature change, we know that the energy is being used to increase the distance between the molecules of the substance and thus to change it from a solid to a liquid or from a liquid to a gas. Such a change is known as a <em>phase change</em>. You might say that latent heat is the energy price that must be paid for a change of state from solid to liquid or from liquid to gas. The energy is not lost; rather, it is stored in the substance as internal energy. The energy price is <q>repaid,</q> so to speak, when the substance changes back from gas to liquid or from liquid to solid. </p>
<figure xml:id="LatentHeat_png"> <caption>Phase Changes</caption> <image source="pics/thermo/LatentHeat.png" width="75%"/>
</figure> 
<p><xref ref="LatentHeat_png"/> shows the relationship between sensible heat and latent heat for one substance, water, at atmospheric pressure. The same kind of chart could be drawn up for other substances; however, different amounts of thermal energy would of course be required for each change of temperature and for each change of physical state. </p>
<p>If we start with 1 pound of ice at 0 °F, we must add 16 BTU in order to raise the temperature of the ice to 32 °F. We call this adding sensible heat. To change the pound of ice at 32 °F to a pound of water at 32 °F, we must add 144 BTU (the <em>latent heat of fusion</em>). There will be no change in temperature while the ice is melting. After all the ice has melted, however, the temperature of the water will be raised as additional heat is supplied. If we add 180 BTU that is, 1 BTU for each degree of temperature between 32 °F and 212 °F the temperature of the water will be raised to the boiling point. To change the pound of water at 212 °F, to a pound of steam at 212 °F, we must add 970 BTU (the <em>latent heat of vaporization</em>). After all the water has been converted to steam, the addition of more heat will cause an increase in the temperature of the steam. If we add approximately 42 BTU to the pound of steam which is at 212 °F, we can superheat it to 300 °F. </p>
<p>The same relationships apply when heat is being removed. The removal of 42 BTU from the pound of steam which is at 300 °F will cause the temperature to drop to 212 °F. As the pound of steam at 212 °F changes to a pound of water at 212 °F, 970 BTU are given off. When a substance is changing from a gas or vapor to a liquid, we usually use the term <em>latent heat of condensation</em> for the heat that is given off. Notice, however, that the latent heat of condensation is exactly the same as the latent heat of vaporization. Only the terms differ to indicate whether a substance is being changed into a liquid or into a gas. The removal of another 180 BTU of sensible heat will lower the temperature of the pound of water from 212 °F to 32 °F. As the pound of water at 32 °F changes to a pound of ice at 32 °F 144 BTU are given off without any accompanying change of temperature. Further removal of heat causes the temperature of the ice to decrease. </p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection  xml:id="" ><title>Specific Heat</title>

<p>In the discussion of sensible heat and latent heat, you may have noticed that it takes only 16 BTU to raise the temperature of 1 pound of ice from 0 °F to 32 °F that is, only 1/2 BTU for each degree of rise in temperature. However, we know that it takes 1 BTU (on the average) to raise the temperature of the same amount of water 1 °F. This difference occurs because the <em>specific heat</em> of water is about twice the specific heat of ice. </p>
<p>Specific heat is a thermal property of matter that must be determined experimentally for each substance. In general, we may say that specific heat is the property of matter; this explains the reason that equal quantities of thermal energy added to two different substances will not necessarily produce the same temperature rise, even when no change of state is involved. The specific heat of a substance is defined as the quantity of heat required to raise the temperature of unit mass of the substance 1 °F. For most engineering applications, specific heat is expressed in BTU per pound per degree Fahrenheit. In metric systems of measurement, specific heat is expressed in calories per gram per degree Celsius. Even though the units of measurement are different in the different systems, the <em>numerical value</em> of specific heat for any given substance is the same in all systems. The specific heat of water is 1.00 in all systems. </p>
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
</section>

<section xml:id=""><title>Energy Transformations</title>
<introduction>
<p>The machinery and equipment in the engineering plant aboard ship is designed either to carry energy from one place to another or to change a substance from one form to another. The principles of energy transformations and some of the important energy changes that occur in the shipboard propulsion cycle are discussed here. </p>
</introduction>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Conservation of Energy</title>

<p>The basic principle dealing with the transformation of energy is the <em>Principle of Conservation of Energy</em>. This principle can be stated in several ways. Most commonly, perhaps, it is stated: <q>Energy can be neither destroyed nor created, but only transformed.</q> Another way to state this principle is: <q>The total quantity of energy in the universe is always the same.</q> Still another way of expressing this principle is by the equation  <me>\mathrm{Energy}_{in} = \mathrm{Energy}_{out}</me>The <q>energy out</q> may be quite different in form from the <q>energy in,</q> but the total amount of energy input must always equal the total amount of energy output. </p>
<p>Another principle, the <em>Principle of Conservation of Matter,</em> states: <q>Matter can be neither created nor destroyed, but only transformed.</q> As you probably know, the development of the atomic bomb demonstrated that matter can be converted into energy; other developments have demonstrated that energy can be converted into matter. Therefore, the Principle of the Conservation of Energy and the Principle of the Conservation of Matter are no longer considered as two parts of a single law or principle but are combined into one principle: “Matter and energy are interchangeable, and the total amount of energy and matter in the universe is constant." </p>
<p>The interchangeability of matter and energy is mentioned here only to point out that the statement <q>energy in must equal energy out</q> is not strictly true for certain situations. However, any noticeable conversion of matter into energy or energy into matter can occur only under very special conditions that we need not consider now. All the energy transformations that we will deal with can be understood quite simply if we consider only the Principle of the Conservation of Energy, that is, <em>Energy in must equal Energy out</em>. </p>
</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Transforming Heat to Work</title>

<p>The energy transformation of primary interest in the shipboard steam plant is the transformation from heat to work. To see how this transformation occurs, we need to consider the pressure, temperature, and volume relationships which hold true for gases. These relationships may be summarized as follows:  
<ul>
 <li> When the temperature is held constant, increasing the pressure on a gas causes a proportional decrease in volume. Decreasing the pressure causes a proportional increase in volume.  </li>
 <li> When the pressure is held constant, increasing the temperature of a gas causes a proportional increase in volume. Decreasing the temperature causes a proportional decrease in volume.  </li>
 <li> When the volume is held constant, increasing the temperature of a gas causes a proportional increase in pressure. Decreasing the temperature causes a proportional decrease in pressure.  </li> 
</ul></p>
<p>Suppose we have a boiler in which steam has just begun to form. With the steam stop valves still closed, the volume of the steam remains constant while the temperature and the pressure are both increasing. When operating pressure is reached and the steam stop valves are opened, the high pressure of the steam causes the steam to flow to the turbines. The pressure of the steam thus provides the potential for doing work; the actual conversion of heat to work is done in the steam turbines. The change in the internal energy (as indicated by changes in pressure and temperature) of the steam between the boiler and the condenser is an indication of the amount of heat that has been converted to work in the turbines. </p>
<p>Since heat is measured in BTU and work is measured in foot-pounds, how can we compare the amount of energy put in as heat with the amount of energy put out as work? At first glance, asking how much heat equals how much work might seem like asking how many lima beans equals playing baseball. However, the problem is not that difficult, since both heat and work are forms of energy. The formula for converting heat to work is  <me>1 \text{ BTU} = 778 \text{ ft-lb}</me> or, in other words, the amount of energy required to raise the temperature of 1 pound of water 1 °F is the same as the amount of energy required to lift a 1-pound weight 778 feet against the force of gravity. </p>
</subsection>

<subsection xml:id="" ><title>Energy Relationships in the Shipboard Propulsion Cycle</title>

<p>The movement of a ship through the water is the result of a number of energy transformations. Although most of these transformations have been mentioned, they have not been discussed in the proper sequence. </p>
<p>The first energy transformation occurs when fuel oil is burned in the boiler furnace. By the process of combustion, the chemical energy stored in the fuel oil is transformed into thermal energy. Thermal energy flows from the burning fuel to the water in the boiler, and steam is generated. The thermal energy is now stored as internal energy in the steam, as we can tell from the increased pressure and temperature of the steam. When the steam is admitted to the turbines, the thermal energy of the steam is converted into mechanical energy, which turns the shaft and drives the ship. Two main energy transformations are involved in converting thermal energy to work in a turbine. First, the thermal energy of the steam is transformed into mechanical kinetic energy (energy of motion) as the steam flows through one or more nozzles. Second, the mechanical kinetic energy of the steam is transformed into work (mechanical energy in transition) as the steam strikes the projecting blades of the turbine and thus causes the turbine to turn. The turning of the turbine rotor causes the propeller shaft to turn also, although at a slower speed, since the turbine is connected to the propeller shaft through reduction gears. The steam exhausts from the turbine to the condenser where it gives up its latent heat of condensation to the circulating seawater. </p>
<p>For the remainder of this cycle, energy is required to get the water (condensate and feedwater) back to the boiler where it will again be heated and changed into steam. The energy used for this purpose is generally the thermal energy of the auxiliary steam. In the case of turbine driven feed pumps, the conversion of thermal energy to mechanical energy occurs in the same way as it does in the case of the propulsion turbines. In the case of motor-driven pumps, the energy conversion is from thermal energy to electrical energy (in a turbogenerator) and then from electrical energy to mechanical energy (work) in the pumps. </p>
<p>As you can see, putting in 1 BTU at the boiler furnace does not mean that 778 foot-pounds of mechanical energy will be available for propelling the ship through the water. Some of the energy put in at the boiler furnace is used by auxiliary machinery such as pumps and forced-draft blowers to supply the boiler with feedwater, fuel oil, and air for combustion. Distilling plants, turbo-generators, steering gears, heating systems, galley and laundry equipment, and many other units throughout the ship use energy derived directly or indirectly from the energy put in at the boiler furnace. </p>
<p>In addition, there are many <q>energy losses</q> throughout the engineering plant. As we have seen, energy cannot actually be lost. But when it is transformed into a form of energy that we cannot use, we say there has been an energy loss. Since no insulation is perfect, some thermal energy is always lost as steam travels through the piping. Friction losses occur in all machinery and piping. There is also an energy loss at the condenser as the steam exhausted from the turbines gives up heat to the circulating seawater and turns into condensate. </p>
<p>Although some energy losses can be partly avoided by designing the machinery and equipment to minimize friction losses, by insulating hot surfaces, and by lubricating moving parts, some energy losses are still unavoidable. Consider, for example, the unavoidable energy loss that occurs at the condenser. To allow the flow of heat, the condenser must be at a lower temperature than the boiler since heat flow can occur only from a higher temperature area to a lower temperature area. Therefore, the energy loss at the condenser is not only unavoidable, but is also actually required for the conversion of heat to work. </p>
<p>As you can see, each BTU that is put in at the boiler furnace has to be divided in many ways before all the energy can be accounted for, but the energy account will always balance. <em>Energy in will always equal Energy out.</em></p>

</subsection>
</section>

<section xml:id=""><title>The Generation of Steam</title>

<p>When a liquid boils, it generates a vapor, that is, some or all of the liquid changes its physical state from liquid to gas (or vapor). As long as the vapor is in contact with the liquid from which it is being generated, it remains at the same temperature as the boiling liquid. In this condition, the liquid and its vapor are said to be in <em>equilibrium contact</em> with each other. </p>
<p>The temperature at which a boiling liquid and its vapor may exist in equilibrium contact depends on the pressure under which the process takes place. As the pressure increases, the boiling temperature increases. As the pressure decreases, the boiling temperature decreases. For each liquid, therefore, the boiling point is determined by the pressure. </p>
<p>When a liquid is boiling and generating vapor, the liquid is called a <em>saturated liquid</em>, and the vapor is called a <em>saturated vapor</em>. The temperature at which a liquid boils under a given pressure is called the <em>saturation temperature</em>, and the corresponding pressure is called the <em>saturation pressure</em>. For each pressure there is a corresponding saturation temperature, and for each temperature there is a corresponding saturation pressure. A few saturation pressures and temperatures for water are listed below. </p>
<p>Atmospheric pressure is 14.7 psia at sea level and lesser at higher altitudes. Trying to cook potatoes at the top of a high mountain takes a great deal longer than it would at sea level. Why is this? As noted before, temperature and pressure are indications of internal energy. Since it is not possible to raise the temperature of the boiling water above the saturation temperature for that pressure, the amount of internal energy available for cooking the potatoes is much less at high altitudes than it is at sea level. By the same line of reasoning, you should be able to figure out why the potatoes cook faster in a pressure cooker than in an open kettle. </p>
<p>A peculiar thing happens to water and steam at an absolute pressure of 3206.2 psia and the corresponding saturation temperature at 705.40 °F. At this point, which is called the <em>critical point,</em> the vapor and the liquid are indistinguishable. No change of state occurs when the pressure is increased above this point or when heat is added. At the critical point, we can no longer refer to <q>water</q> or <q>steam,</q> since we cannot tell the water and steam apart. Instead, the substance is merely called a <q>fluid</q> or a <q>working substance.</q> Boilers designed to operate at pressures and temperatures above the critical point are called <em>supercritical</em> boilers. Supercritical boilers are not used, at present, in propulsion plants of ships; however, some boilers of this type are used in stationary steam power plants. </p>
<p>If we generate steam by boiling water in an open pan at atmospheric pressure, the water and the steam which is in immediate contact with the water will remain at 212 °F until all the water has been evaporated. If we fit an absolutely tight cover to the pan, so that no steam can escape while we continue to add heat, both the pressure and the temperature inside the vessel will rise. The steam and water will both increase in temperature and pressure, and each fluid will be at the same temperature and pressure as the other. </p>
<p>In operation, a boiler is neither an open vessel nor a closed vessel. Instead, it is a vessel designed with restricted openings which allow steam to escape at a uniform rate while feedwater is being brought in at a uniform rate. After boiler operating pressure has been reached, therefore, the process of steam generation in a boiler takes place at constant pressure and constant temperature, if we disregard any fluctuations that may be caused by changes in steam demands. </p>
<p>Although it is impossible to raise the temperature of the steam in the steam drum above the temperature of the water from which it is being generated, we can raise the temperature of the steam if we first remove the steam from contact with the water inside the steam drum and then add heat. Steam which has been heated above its saturation temperature for any given pressure is called <em>superheated steam</em>, and the vessel in which the saturated steam is superheated is called a <em>superheater.</em>The amount by which the temperature of the superheated steam exceeds the temperature of saturated steam at the same pressure is known as the <em>degree of superheat</em>. For example, if saturated steam at a pressure of 620 psia and the corresponding saturation temperature of 490 °F is superheated to 790 °F, the degree of superheat is 300 °F. </p>
<p>All ship’s propulsion boilers are equipped with superheaters. The primary advantage is that superheating the steam provides a greater temperature differential between the boiler and the condenser, thus allowing more heat to be converted to work at the turbines. Another advantage is that superheated steam is dry and therefore causes relatively little corrosion or erosion of machinery and piping. Also, superheated steam does not conduct heat as rapidly (and therefore does not lose heat as rapidly) as saturated steam. The increased efficiency which results from the use of superheated steam reduces the amount of fuel oil required to generate each pound of steam, and so reduces the space and weight requirements for the boilers. </p>
<p>It should be noted, however, that most auxiliary machinery is designed to operate on saturated steam. Reciprocating machinery in particular requires saturated steam for the lubrication of internal moving parts of the steam end. Ship’s boilers, therefore, are designed to produce both saturated steam and superheated steam. </p>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter xml:id="introElectricty"> 
<title>Electricity</title>
<p><term>Voltage</term>, or <em>electric potential difference</em>, is a fundamental concept in electricity.  Voltage  is measured in units of volts (V), and symbolized as <m>V</m>.  Voltage can be seen as the <q>push</q> or<q>force</q> that propels electric charges within a circuit. When voltage is applied to a circuit, it creates an electric field that influences the movement of charged particles, resulting in the establishment of an electric current. In simpler terms, voltage serves as the driving force behind the flow of electric charges in an electrical system.</p>
<p>Voltage can be produced through several methods, including <em>chemical reactions</em> (such as in batteries) and the <em>photovoltaic effect</em> (as in solar cells). However, the most important method of is <term>electromagnetic induction</term>.  Electromagnetic induction is the process where a changing magnetic field induces (creates) an electric voltage in a nearby conductor.   This phenomenon is the basis for generating electricity in devices like generators and transformers.  Electrical generators will be described in more detail in <xref provisional="generators"/></p>
<p><term>Current</term> refers to the flow of electric charge in an electrical circuit. It is the rate at which electric charges, typically electrons, move through a <term>conductor</term>. Current is measured in amperes (A) and is represented by the symbol <m>I</m>. It can be thought of as the quantity of charge passing through a point in a circuit per unit of time. The flow of current occurs when there is a potential difference (voltage) applied across a conductor, providing the driving force for the movement of electric charges.</p>
<p><term>Resistance</term> is a property of a material or component in an electrical circuit that opposes the flow of electric current. It is measured in ohms (Ω) and is denoted by the symbol <m>R</m>. Resistance determines the extent to which a material or device hinders the flow of electrical charge. When a voltage is applied across a conductor, the resistance restricts the flow of current, resulting in a decrease in the magnitude of the current. Materials with high resistance impede the flow of electricity more than materials with low resistance. The resistance of a component depends on factors such as its length, cross-sectional area, and the material it is made of.</p>
<p><term>Ohm’s law</term> describes the relationship between current, voltage, and resistance. According to Ohm's Law, the current flowing through a circuit is directly proportional to the voltage across it and inversely proportional to the resistance of the circuit. Mathematically, this relationship is expressed as <me>I = V/R</me>  where: <ul marker="">
<li><m>I</m> is the the current in amperes</li>
<li><m>V</m> is the voltage in volts, and </li>
<li><m>R</m> is the resistance in ohms (Ω). </li>
</ul></p>
<p>In other words, an increase in voltage leads to a corresponding increase in current if the resistance remains constant, while an increase in resistance results in a decrease in current for a given voltage.</p>
<p>An <term>electrical circuit</term> is a complete loop or path that allows for the regulated flow of electric current to power devices and carry out different tasks. It consists of different elements like voltage sources, switches, and electrical loads that are interconnected through wires. <term>Electrical loads</term> refer to devices that consume electrical energy and convert it into another form like mechanical work, light, or heat.   Motors, light bulbs and heating elements are some common examples of electrical loads.  </p>
<p><term>Series Circuit</term>: In a series circuit, the components are connected in a single path such that the same current flows through each component. The components are connected end-to-end, creating a sequential circuit. In a series circuit, the total resistance is the sum of the individual resistances, and the total voltage across the circuit is divided among the components. If one component fails or is disconnected, the entire circuit is broken, and the flow of current stops.</p>

<p><term>Parallel Circui</term>t: In a parallel circuit, the components are connected in multiple paths, allowing the current to divide and flow through different branches simultaneously. Each component in a parallel circuit has the same voltage across it. The total current in the circuit is divided among the branches based on the resistance of each branch. If one component fails or is disconnected in a parallel circuit, the current can still flow through the remaining branches.</p>

<p>In summary, a series circuit has components connected in a single path with the same current flowing through each component, while a parallel circuit has components connected in multiple paths, allowing current to divide among the branches.</p>
<paragraphs><title>Electrical Power</title>
<paragraphs><title>DC Power</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>AC Single phasePower</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>AC Three phase power</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Active Power, reactive power, power factor</title></paragraphs>
</paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Overview of Circuits</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Electrical Symbols</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Diodes</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Transisters</title></paragraphs>

<section xml:id=""><title>Electrical Safety</title></section>
</chapter>

<chapter xml:id="piping-systems"> 
<title>Piping Systems</title>
<section xml:id=""><title>Pipe</title></section>

<section xml:id=""><title>Valves</title></section>

<section xml:id=""><title>Pumps</title></section>

<section xml:id=""><title>Process and Instrument Diagrams</title>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter xml:id="steam-power"> 
<title>Steam Power</title>
<paragraphs><title>Main Steam Cycle -Adapt and edit form Intro to Steam Ch 1</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Construction</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Operations</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Steam Turbines</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Power Transmission and Gearing</title></paragraphs>

</chapter>

<chapter xml:id="diesel-power"> 
<title>Diesel Power</title>
<paragraphs><title>Combustion Engines</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Gas vs. Diesel Engines and  Otto vs. Diesel Cycle</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Engine Construction and Components</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Two Stroke vs. Four Stroke</title></paragraphs>
</chapter>

<chapter xml:id="Electric-power"> 
<title>Electrical Power</title>
<section xml:id=""><title>Propulsion System</title>
<paragraphs><title>Motors</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Generators</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Variable Frequency Drives</title></paragraphs>
</section>

<section xml:id=""><title>Electrical Distribution</title>
<paragraphs><title>Transformers</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Circuit breakers</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Safety Devices</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Overcurrent Protection</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Switchgear</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>One Line Diagram</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Energy Management System</title></paragraphs>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter xml:id="auxiliary-systems"> 
<title>Auxiliary Systems</title>
<section xml:id=""><title>Lubrication systems</title>
<paragraphs><title>Requirements of a Lubrication System</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Rotating Machinery</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Axial and Radial Bearings</title></paragraphs>
</section>

<section xml:id=""><title>Fuel oil systems</title></section>

<section xml:id=""><title>Cooling Systems</title></section>
</chapter>

<chapter xml:id="refrigeration"> 
<title>Refrigeration</title></chapter>

<chapter xml:id="fresh-water"> 
<title>Fresh Water</title></chapter>

<chapter xml:id="sewage-treatment"> 
<title>Sewage Treatment</title></chapter>

<chapter xml:id="TSPS"> 
<title>TS Patriot State</title>
<paragraphs><title>Vessel Particulars</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>Chapter 14 - MMA Sea Term I</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>What to expect on the training cruise</title></paragraphs>

<paragraphs><title>System diagrams</title></paragraphs>
</chapter>
</book>
</pretext>